<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<kb>
 <nepenthes synset="nepenthes.n.01">
  <s>
   You can use undrained containers as pots, but be prepared to water frequently. One exception to the above rule is the Dewy Pine (Drosophyllum) which prefers to be in a large terracotta pot. Mexican Pinguicula can be grown in a much more diverse range of planters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes, Heliamphora, Cephalotus and Drosophyllum want to be watered frequently but do not want to dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cephalotus dislike long periods of being waterlogged, so it is best to allow the water in the tray to evaporate before adding more.
  </s>
  <s>
   Plastic containers are best, but nepenthes also do well in glazed terracotta or glazed clay.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use drained containers; shallow un-drained containers will rot nepenthes's roots.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cephalotus does best with moderately warm summers and cool to chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plants may die in long periods of very hot weather and nepenthes enjoy cool summer nights.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes require at least three hours of direct light if grown indoors on a windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you notice your plant has stopped making pitchers, it is often a sign that the plant needs a bit more light. In greenhouses avoid the tray method of watering entirely and place the containers on benches or hang nepenthes so water can freely drain away.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes do not require any dormancy period. Lowlanders come from low elevations in tropical Southeast Asia.
  </s>
  <s>
   Darlingtonia is an enigmatic plant native to Oregon and California.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are native to SE Asia, and these plants come in many shapes and sizes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most of the 170+ Nepenthes species are found in Southeast Asia - particularly Borneo, Sumatra, and the Philippines - and the genus ranges from highland montane plants to those inhabiting steamy lowland jungles.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes's cross-fertile nature has resulted in countless unique hybrids, both in cultivation and in the wild. These include male and female parentage (remember that Nepenthes are dioecious!)
  </s>
  <s>
   There are a nice selection of Nepenthes suitable for beginners, as well as growing supplies like compost and pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are a fantastic range of Nepenthes species and hybrids suitable for growers of all abilities.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you’re not sure what species you’ve got, you could try putting it into the Nepenthes Species Identifier online.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do you grow Nepenthes?
  </s>
  <s>
   The genus Nepenthes has the only species known to have devoured whole rats!
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes usually grow as climbing or scrambling vines.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most species are found in Southeast Asia, Nepenthes's center of distribution being the island of Borneo.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are not typically jungle plants, but prefer more open and sunny ridges, slopes and stunted forests.
  </s>
  <s>
   Seventy percent of Nepenthes are tropical highland or mountain plants, growing at elevations of 3,000 to 10,000 feet above sea level.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are both Highland Nepenthes and Lowland Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes The Monkey Cup plant (Nepenthes) belongs to the Nepenthaceae family and is a tropical plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Nepenthes got its name from its unique appearance and large ‘cups’.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because Nepenthes eats insects, it is a carnivorous plant species.
  </s>
  <s>
   At the bottom of the cup of the Nepenthes is a viscous liquid full of digestive juices (enzymes).
  </s>
  <s>
   Some cups of nepenthes species can grow up to 50cm tall!
  </s>
  <s>
   The Nepenthes can be found in different parts of the world and is mostly found in Southeast Asia (Borneo). In addition, the plant species can be found in Sri Lanka, Madagascar and Seychelles.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most Nepenthes grow in tropical slope forests.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are Nepenthes plants that can be found at altitudes of up to 3,000 metres. These are ‘highland’ Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   A climbing Nepenthes in nature can grow up to 15 metres tall.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes likes sun very much.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Nepenthes plant can also grow beautiful yellow / brown flowers in the form of clusters.
  </s>
  <s>
   The ‘Cup’ trap is used by Nepenthes (Monkey Cup plant), amongst others.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes is found in Jungles all over the world.
  </s>
  <s>
   Ranging in size from diminutive miniatures like Nepenthes argentii to gargantuan monstrosities like Nepenthes rajah, the genus includes the only carnivorous plants known to have caught and eaten whole rats.
  </s>
  <s>
   The genus is hugely diverse, and some species have stricter temperature requirements than others.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most cultivation advice is broadly applicable to all Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are over 170 species of Nepenthes, plus countless natural and cultivated hybrids.
  </s>
  <s>
   High-powered fluorescent or LED lights (such as T5 growlights) work very well with Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve found that LEDs growlights can be particularly effective since nepenthes tend to give off less heat than fluorescent bulbs.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes maxima can thrive in a terrarium.
  </s>
  <s>
   Note that Nepenthes do not require a winter dormancy, but if you’re growing under natural light, the shorter daylight hours will often slow your plant down significantly.
  </s>
  <s>
   Each Nepenthes species grows best at the temperatures it experiences in its natural habitat. These temperatures correspond to the altitudes at which nepenthes grow in the wild.
  </s>
  <s>
   Remember that Nepenthes are tropical montane plants, and so most require some kind of temperature drop at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes villosa, grown by Simon Lumb, is an example of a true highlander.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes bicalarata at Chester Zoo, is an example of a true lowlander.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many Nepenthes hybrids are particularly tolerant of lower humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are quite adaptable to lower levels, as long as the growing media is kept moist.
  </s>
  <s>
   When you first start growing Nepenthes, space probably won’t be at the top of your list. Small plants often grow slowly and may take a while to adapt to the conditions of nepenthes's new home.
  </s>
  <s>
   Remember that Nepenthes can get very large and will produce climbing vines - these will need to be pruned!
  </s>
  <s>
   A greenhouse heated to a minimum of 12°C and covered with shade cloth is undoubtedly the best way to grow a wide variety of highland Nepenthes species on a large scale.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers create warm chambers within nepenthes's greenhouses for lowlanders.
  </s>
  <s>
   Species and Hybrids There are over 170 known species of Nepenthes, and more are described each year.
  </s>
  <s>
   All of nepenthes are cross-fertile with one another to at least some degree.
  </s>
  <s>
   Note that Nepenthes hybrids are often easier growers than pure species plants (on account of so-called ‘hybrid vigour’).
  </s>
  <s>
   For now, I’ll recommend some easy-to-grow hybrids and species: Nepenthes x ventrata, Nepenthes 'Bloody Mary', and Nepenthes 'Gaya'.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve found Nepenthes rajah and Nepenthes attenboroughii to benefit from a more ultramafic substrate - mine grow well in a mixture of peat moss, perlite, and kanuma.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the UK, South West Carnivorous Plants offers both a ready-made Nepenthes compost, and components for mixing your own (e.g.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are more tolerant of water impurities and dissolved minerals than other carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   My recommended foods for Venus flytraps will all work, but dried crickets are particularly suitable for Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   For experienced growers with larger collections, you could also try Osmocote Flower and Vegetable pellets - I tried these following a recommendation from Peter D’Amato, and my plants seemed to enjoy them.
  </s>
  <s>
   In my experience, the most effective food for Nepenthes is a water-soluble seaweed-based fertiliser, mixed in a spray bottle and squirted into the pitchers every few weeks.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes truncata x ephippiata are known to catch mice!
  </s>
  <s>
   Unlike many other carnivores, Nepenthes can also benefit from foliar fertilisation.
  </s>
  <s>
   When grown in the northern hemisphere, Nepenthes don’t always flower on a regular schedule like plants native to temperate climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   It varies by species, but in my experience many mature Nepenthes grown under natural light will flower in the Autumn.
  </s>
  <s>
   You’ll know when a Nepenthes is about to flower when it produces an infloresence before its next leaf.
  </s>
  <s>
   One of the many fascinating things about Nepenthes is that nepenthes are dioecious, meaning all individual plants are either male or female! This is extremely unusual among plants, which normally have both male and female reproductive parts in nepenthes's flowers (pollen from anthers, and a female stigma).
  </s>
  <s>
   The New Nepenthes series includes countless expedition reports, conservation assessments and wild observations that underpin the treatment and taxonomy presented here.
  </s>
 </nepenthes>
 <sarracenia synset="sarracenia.n.01">
  <s>
   Organic does not mean non-toxic. Mealybugs can look like cotton fluff in the growth points of your Sarracenia or at the base of Nepenthes leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Clean off any old growth; trim leaves back, remove old scales of leaves at the rhizome of Sarracenia and cut back any dying or dead growth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Powdery Mildew is similar looking to botrytis but is not as fluffy and is very common on Sarracenia. Sulphur is the best treatment for powdery mildew, follow directions on the packaging for application.
  </s>
  <s>
   SOOTY MOLD: Commonly seen on Sarracenia this looks just like it sounds; like a black mold all over the pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sometimes the lids of Sarracenia will slightly burn, this is the sweet nectar burning a bit in the hot sun, it is totally normal and nothing to worry about.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you live in a very hot, dry and sunny area, like Arizona, it will be best to grow sarracenia in full morning sun with protection from the afternoon sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always keep sarracenia sitting in a saucer with a few inches of distilled or purified water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not let sarracenia dry out.
  </s>
 </sarracenia>
 <drosera synset="drosera.n.01">
  <s>
   You can use MaxSea on Nepenthes, Drosera, Venus Flytraps, Sarracenia, Darlintonia, Heliamphora, Cephalotus and Drosophyllum. Use caution and lower concentrations when fertilizing more finicky South African sundews like Drosera regia, glabripes and slackii.
  </s>
  <s>
   Often, Pinguicula and Drosera will catch many adult insects and help reduce the population.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sundews (Drosera) prefer full to part sun.
  </s>
 </drosera>
 <flytrap synset="flytrap.n.01">
  <s>
   To feed Venus flytrap traps, use live mealworms (usually available at pet stores) or other live bugs.
  </s>
  <s>
   Use a pair of tongs or tweezers to feed the insect or worm to the trap, triggering the trigger hairs to cause the trap to close.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant can be triggered to close but often the trap will reopen in a day or two, which indicates that it has not completed digestion.
  </s>
  <s>
   THRIPS: Sarracenia are a favorite of thrips; flytrap's chewing causes silvery patches on the pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dogs are easily dissuaded when pots are relocated to high spots.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use distilled, reverse osmosis or rain water only. The water vending machines at your local grocery store are a good, inexpensive source for pure water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Brita and Pur water filters do not remove enough dissolved salts to make much difference.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is good to routinely check the TDS of this water source as these levels can fluctuate with the seasonal droughts.Most carnivorous plants love being in water!
  </s>
  <s>
   Especially important on the hottest days, be sure to check your water levels frequently in the summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY: These are warm-temperate plants meaning that flytrap need warm summers and chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be grown in terrariums under bright fluorescent light, we recommend a fixture with four T5 bulbs or LEDs.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Mexican varieties can be kept on the tray system with overhead watering while flytraps have carnivorous foliage in summer and autumn.
  </s>
  <s>
   These are best in light-colored, preferably white, plastic or glazed ceramic pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   Single plants grow well in six- to eight-inch pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   When reducing watering, reduce watering so that it slowly goes dry over the course of a month.
  </s>
  <s>
   Keep flytraps in a cool, dry place during summer dormancy and sprinkle flytrap with water once every couple of weeks. As sundews grow worldwide, flytrap come from varied climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many flytraps can be grown easily on a sunny windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrariums with high-powered fluorescent lights are easy to set up and ideal; we recommend four T-5 lights.
  </s>
  <s>
   In terrariums and on windowsills, place the pot in a shallow saucer and water overhead as soon as the water in the saucer evaporates.
  </s>
  <s>
   Don't allow the pot to sit in deep water for extended periods of time as this can lead to root rot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Constant temperatures in 80's F with high humidity is ideal, although some species will grow on sunny windowsills in warm homes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most highlanders can be easily grown on sunny windowsills.
  </s>
  <s>
   For instance, we recommend against using terracotta or un-glazed ceramic for most carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   While some species may adapt to life on a windowsill, most prefer a greenhouse or terrarium.
  </s>
  <s>
   Native to North Carolina, the Venus Flytrap likes full sun during summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grow flytraps on a sunny windowsill with partial to dappled sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can take full sun, so grow it in the sunniest window in your home.
  </s>
  <s>
   As with all plants, the key to successfully growing Nepenthes in cultivation is the ability to replicate the conditions of flytrap's natural habitat.
  </s>
  <s>
   If your flytrap's leaves are turning black, don't panic - traps can die for many different reasons and this is rarely fatal to the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Struggling with your flytrap?
  </s>
  <s>
   Besgrow Spagmoss has naturally low concentrations of soluble salts, is virtually sterile and can hold up to 20 times its weight in water.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant can be kept in both a hanging pot and an upright pot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous plants come in every shape and size, and each species has a different appearance and a different lure method.
  </s>
  <s>
   The ‘Clap’ trap is used by the best-known carnivorous plant, the Venus Flytrap.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the Venus Flytrap's mouth there are three to nine hairs.
  </s>
  <s>
   When an insect lands in this trap and touches one of these hairs – twice – within 20 seconds, the trap closes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Once the insect lands on the trap, it sticks to it.
  </s>
  <s>
   Old traps are best to be removed.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is best to remove the flowers if traps don’t develop as flytraps should (unless, of course, you find the flowers extra beautiful).
  </s>
  <s>
   In the northern hemisphere that could be an east or west-facing window which receives direct sun for only part of the day, or a greenhouse with 50% shade cloth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Too much direct sun can burn flytrap's leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many of these will grow quite happily on a cool windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grow Tents: Providing you can maintain good humidity levels and avoid your lights overheating the interior of the tent, these can be a great way to grow a variety of species and hybrids.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you wish to grow highland and ultra-highland species but struggle to provide the necessary low temperatures, some enthusiasts have success cooling flytrap's tents at night with specially-adapted freezers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use pots with plenty of drainage holes.
  </s>
 </flytrap>
 <utricularia synset="utricularia.n.01">
  <s>
   When the Pinguicula has formed these tight, succulent leaves you can withhold water as described above for the dormancy period.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical Bladderworts (Utricularia) are all from the Caribbean, Central America, and South America.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrestrial Bladderworts (Utricularia) are easy to grow and produce profusions of flowers. The flowers of the Pinguicula are an exception to this.
  </s>
 </utricularia>
 <seed synset="seeded_player.n.01">
  <s>
   We recommend treating with Monterey Garden Spray, the main ingredient is Spinosad. You will need to treat the plant at least twice, 1 week apart.
  </s>
  <s>
   A good mix is two parts lava rock, and or pumice to one part peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you do have hard water, it is best to use collected rain water, distilled water, reverse osmosis water, or de-ionized water.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is common for several traps to "burn" and die back when you first put them into the sun, they are just getting used to the full sun exposure and will quickly grow new traps.
  </s>
  <s>
   They thrive in temperatures ranging from 20 degrees - 90 F degrees and can take a freeze or high temperature spike up to 110 F degrees for a brief period.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you live in an area with very cold winters, where night time temperatures drop below 20 degrees for sustained periods, you have options for providing them with a winter dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dormancy is triggered by a combination of exposure to shorter photo periods and cooler temperatures in the 50-60's F.  While you can skip a dormancy period once or twice, long term your plant will begin to do poorly and will eventually die if you skip this crucial period. You can bring your plant indoors to a sunny windowsill in an unheated room or garage where the night time temperatures will dip down into the 50-60 F.  Leave it sitting in water during this period and put it outside again when outside temperatures increase.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to pack at least four inches of mulch on top of the plants and all around the sides to prevent winds from chilling seed.
  </s>
  <s>
   Our tropical species do best in warm greenhouses and terrariums.
  </s>
  <s>
   The warm temperate species from the U.S. tolerate light frost and brief freezes.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown on cool, sunny windowsills sometimes, but the best plants are grown in climate controlled greenhouses or terrariums where day temps remain in the 70's F and night time temps in the 40's to 50's F.Because of their need for temperature control we recommend specific containers.
  </s>
  <s>
   A few prefer to be waterlogged.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are not tolerant of low temperatures.
  </s>
  <s>
   They thrive in temperatures ranging from 20 degrees - 90 F degrees and can take a freeze or high temperature spike up to 100 F degrees for a brief period.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most carnivorous plants - including Venus flytraps - are native to temperate climates, and seed survive the winters by entering a resting phase.
  </s>
  <s>
   Species that grow below 3,000 feet are considered lowland.
  </s>
  <s>
   Inside the cup itself are sturdy hairs that are pointed downwards.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not give carnivorous plants tap water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some carnivorous plants grow flowers.
  </s>
  <s>
   It’s difficult to offer generalised advice on growing locations which is applicable to all species!
  </s>
  <s>
   In my experience, it’s also possible for humidity to be too high! This is worth bearing in mind if you opt for a terrarium or other enclosed space.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some easy-to-grow species and cultivars can adapt to the lower humidity of a bright windowsill, providing seed's other requirements are met.
  </s>
  <s>
   Paired with T5 growlights, a large terrarium can be a great way to grow young plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are many thousands of unique hybrids in cultivation, from simple primary hybrids to extraordinarily complex mixtures of dozens of species.
  </s>
  <s>
   As such, don’t limit yourself to just species when looking to start your collection - in fact, starting with hybrids is often a good choice.
  </s>
  <s>
   For UK growers, I highly recommend South West Carnivorous Plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   For long-term healthy growth, stick to rainwater, distilled or deionised water, or water purified using a reverse-osmosis (RO) system.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you are growing your Nepenthes where they will not be able to catch their own food, dried insects can be dropped into the pitchers every few weeks.
  </s>
  <s>
   There is a reason why species seed is seldom produced in cultivation - even if you are a skilled enough grower to have multiple mature specimens of the same species in flower at the same time, there’s no guarantee you’ll have a male and a female.
  </s>
 </seed>
 <care synset="care.n.04">
  <s>
   Live prey will stimulate the trap to close tightly, seal and emit the digestive fluids needed to break down the insect.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can use a cotton swab dipped in medicinal alcohol (the kind used in first aid kits) to swab in between leaves on the rhizome, or any other nooks and crannies where you see evidence of mealy bug.
  </s>
  <s>
   Fungus loves fresh new growth in particular. This can be combatted with increased light, better airflow and reducing overhead watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   Luckily carnivorous plants are non-toxic to our beloved pets.
  </s>
  <s>
   Depending on the persistence of your cat you may need to relocate your plants to an inaccessbile shelf or into a terrarium indoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   Basically the soil mix should be airy and the rock ingredients will help cool the roots.
  </s>
  <s>
   The soil mix should be airy and the rock ingredients will help keep the mix open and cool.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can take light frost and brief freezes.
  </s>
  <s>
   They should be brought in or protected during long freezes below 25 F.  Ours plants take night time temps of 25 F without damage, as long as it warms back up during the day. Unlike most carnivores, Dewy Pines need to be kept a little on the dry side.
  </s>
  <s>
   All pots must have drainage holes!
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use distilled, reverse osmosis or rain water only.
  </s>
  <s>
   These plants are especially sensitive to care's water quality and it is very important to give care mineral and salt free water.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend live meal worms available from any pet store.
  </s>
  <s>
   Charles Darwin called the Venus flytrap “the most wonderful plant in the world”.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use distilled, reverse osmosis or rain water only.
  </s>
  <s>
   These plants are especially sensitive to care's water quality and it is very important to give care mineral and salt free water. These are warm-temperate plants meaning that care need warm summers and chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Whether you’re a long-time greenhouse grower or simply curious about carnivorous plants, Tom’s Carnivores has something for you.
  </s>
  <s>
   They experience hot days, warm nights, and continuous high humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Above the lowland heat of the rainforest, the mountain climate can be considerably cooler and wetter, especially at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the orchid growing industry, it is renowned for having long, strong strands, great longevity, high rot resistance, and peerless water-holding capacity.
  </s>
  <s>
   The combination of long strands and high water-permeability ensures strong and healthy root development.
  </s>
  <s>
   Naturally Sustainable &amp; RenewableBesgrow Spagmoss is hand-picked and naturally air dried to ensure its purity and to guarantee its remarkable water holding capacity (maximum WHC of 96%).
  </s>
  <s>
   The function of the smooth edge is that an insect has no grip and therefore slides into the cup.
  </s>
  <s>
   The fly trap manifests itself in the shape of a mouth.
  </s>
  <s>
   The cup has an attractive colour and produces an attractive smell that lures insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   When selecting a location for your Nepenthes, there are four main things to consider: Light, Temperature, Humidity, and Space.
  </s>
  <s>
   Artificial light is an option.
  </s>
  <s>
   Humidity should ideally be quite high - at least 50% relative humidity (RH) during the daytime, and higher at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers have success using a misting bottle daily to raise humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Regular light watering can help to raise humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. maxima have red patterning on a green background with a large, flamboyant red peristome (lip).
  </s>
  <s>
   You should aim to take care of all your plant’s other needs (lighting, temperature, humidity, and so on) before thinking about feeding &amp; fertilisation.
  </s>
 </care>
 <dionaea synset="dionaea.n.01">
  <s>
   Venus Flytrap (Dionaea) require full sun.
  </s>
 </dionaea>
 <sundew synset="sundew.n.01">
  <s>
   These plants have a very shallow root system. Because of this, sundew can be grown in small, shallow planters with no drainage.
  </s>
  <s>
   We find sundew can be potted into teacups, vintage pottery, seashells, on lava rocks and other novelty planters.
  </s>
  <s>
   MaxSea may be used from seedlings to mature sundews.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be careful to wet perlite before use as breathing in perlite dust can be harmful. Pumice can be found in many hardware stores and specialty nurseries. Lava rock can be used if it is a small grade of lava rock, about the size of a pea.
  </s>
  <s>
   All carnivorous plants should be grown with a pure, low mineral water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican or Tropical Butterworts are great for a sunny windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   When grown under high intensity fluorescent grow lights many of sundew will blush so that the entire plant is glowing pink or red!
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm Temperate Butterworts do well outdoors in part sun to full sun with a bit of protection from afternoon sun. All temperate and warm temperate species should be grown permanently wet on the tray system, with frequent overhead watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can usually tell how dry a species enjoys its winter by the size of its succulent leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   We wait for the butterworts to go dormant before we stop watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   When sundew begin growing sundew's carnivorous leaves we begin the tray method of watering again.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not worry too much about providing dormancy; if your plants do not start to grow the succulent type leaves, which look very different than sundew's regular leaves, you do not need to withhold water. For temperate species use a mix of two parts peat, one part sand, and one part perlite.
  </s>
  <s>
   Flowering plants should be kept a bit drier.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most species of sundew require at least six hours of direct light to thrive.
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm-temperate and sub-tropical sundews do well on windowsills, in cool greenhouses, or terrariums and appreciate cool nights.
  </s>
  <s>
   Winter growing sundews from Australia and South Africa could be grown outdoors in a Mediterranean climate without frost or in a cool greenhouse.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrestrial bladderworts will grow happily alongside many carnivorous plants in bogs.
  </s>
  <s>
   Hardy Sundews are native to the United States.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sundews are a plant with dewy, sticky leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many sundews grow well as regular houseplants with partial sunlight.
  </s>
  <s>
   At the top of the inside of Monkey cup plant’s leaf is a smooth edge. At the bottom of the trap is a watery secretion that digests and converts the prey into food.
  </s>
  <s>
   The ‘Sticky’ trap:This trap is used by Drosera (Sundew) and Pinguicula (Butterwort), among others.
  </s>
  <s>
   The lime contained in tap water is bad for carnivorous plants and can cause lime build-up in the long term.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many common hybrids are extremely tolerant growers and make excellent houseplants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Spindly leaves and a lack of colouration are signs of insufficient light, while blotchy red marks can be a sign your plant is getting more than enough light.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ‘Bloody Mary’ is a popular cultivar for terrariums, as a beautiful hybrid between N. ventricosa and N. ampullaria.
  </s>
  <s>
   During the spring and summer, spraying your plant with a weak solution of high-quality orchid fertiliser several times a month can help promote good growth.
  </s>
 </sundew>
 <pitcher synset="pitcher.n.05">
  <s>
   No myths.
  </s>
  <s>
   Outdoor perennials include Darlingtonia: Cobra Plant, Dionaea: Venus Flytraps, Drosera: Hardy Sundews, Pinguicula: Hardy Butterworts and Sarracenia: American Pitcher Plants
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical plants include Cephalotus: Australian Pitcher, Drosera: Tropical Sundews, Heliamphora: Sun Pitchers, Nepenthes: Asian Pitchers, and Pinguicula: Mexican Butterworts
  </s>
  <s>
   We prefer small plastic pots with holes in the bottom, so that the tray watering method may be used.
  </s>
  <s>
   Healthy plants that have access to lots of prey don't necessarily need any fertilizing, although it would still be beneficial.
  </s>
  <s>
   Feeding a dead insect or inert food, such as hamburger, is less likely to trigger the full digestive process of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant needs the live prey to stimulate this full process or it will reopen, thinking it has caught an inert and indigestible item.
  </s>
  <s>
   Scale look like little waxy scabs that encrust the leaves and stems. Scale may be wiped away with rubbing alcohol on a Q-tip or cotton pad. Badly infested leaves may be cut away and thrown in the trash.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nectar mold feeds on the sugary nectar of the pitcher plants. It can often be wiped off of the pitchers with a damp paper towel and requires no treatment.
  </s>
  <s>
   Algae can grow in the trays of plants over time and is nonharmful but cleaning your trays once a month will inhibit this growth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dogs can knock over pots and very rarely eat a plant or two.
  </s>
  <s>
   Zero Water pitchers will filter water enough and are an easy way to make small amounts of distilled water.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be watered using the tray method.
  </s>
  <s>
   Simply put your plants, while in the pot, into a deep tray and fill it with pure water.
  </s>
  <s>
   They will thrive in full sun, meaning at least six hours of direct light.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can grow pitcher indoors on a very, very sunny windowsill or in a terrarium under grow lights but pitcher generally do best outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you see black mold on your pitcher, don't panic! This harmless mold grows on the pitcher nectar, and it is not harmful to your plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Although some consider it unsightly, black mold is totally normal and occurs on both plants in the wild and in cultivation.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are tolerant of brief, light frost down to 25 F degrees, but may be killed in lower temperatures.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most terrestrials also do well in un-drained containers.
  </s>
  <s>
   The tighter, smaller leafed rosettes such a Pinguicula gypsicola or the bulb-like heterophylla and macrophylla require bone-dry conditions.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the spring and summer, large plants should be allowed to dry slightly before you water again.
  </s>
  <s>
   Wilting will damage roots and set the plant back.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dewy Pines are mediterranean natives.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sun Pitchers (Heliamphora) like bright light.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown with less light, but pitchers will remain much greener.
  </s>
  <s>
   As summer approaches wait for the plant to quickly go brown.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical Pitcher Plants (Nepenthes) enjoy very bright, diffused light or partly sunny conditions.
  </s>
  <s>
   Put one pellet into each new pitcher as it opens.
  </s>
  <s>
   They will thrive in full sun, meaning at least six hours of direct light.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can grow pitcher indoors on a very, very sunny windowsill or in a terrarium under grow lights but pitcher generally do best outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you grow pitcher indoors be sure to provide pitcher with a winter dormancy. Always keep pitchers sitting in a saucer with a few inches of distilled or purified water, pitchers do not want to dry out but try not to flood the top of the traps with water as they do not appreciate this.
  </s>
  <s>
   Never let pitchers dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   MaxSea is a nice, mild, kelp-based food that won't burn your plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   In winter, it goes dormant.
  </s>
  <s>
   The American Pitcher Plant comes in many shapes, sizes, and colors.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sarracenia prefer full sun in spring and summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pitcher plants go dormant in winter and like full to partial sun during summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   In winter, pitcher plants drop their leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sarracenia grows best where summers are mild.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pinguicula are tropical plants with sticky, succulent-like leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes lamii are from New Guinea.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’d highly recommend The Savage Garden, by Peter D’Amato.
  </s>
  <s>
   If there is a royalty among carnivorous plants, that distinction surely lies with the Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical pitcher plants have a rich botanical and horticultural history and the plants pitcherselves are a virtual ecosystem of give-and-take with nature.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are hauntingly beautiful; their pitcher traps often as elaborate and gaudy as artistic creations by humankind.
  </s>
  <s>
   This exotic carnivorous plant has a beautifully coloured cup shape and is therefore also called ‘Monkey Cup plant’.
  </s>
  <s>
   Their native forests have large temperature differences.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are also Monkey cup plants that grow in the wet lowlands.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is important that the plant is not in direct sunlight.
  </s>
  <s>
   The pitcher plant likes humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is important that the plant has space.
  </s>
  <s>
   Unlike the Venus flytrap and the Trumpet pitcher plant, Nepenthes does not need to hibernate.
  </s>
  <s>
   The carnivorous plant family has evolved to survive by luring insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous plants can be found all over the world.
  </s>
  <s>
   Similar to the cup trap, the pitcher trap produces an attractive liquid and beautiful colour that attracts insects. Inside the trap are small vertical slits that prevent the insect from escaping.
  </s>
  <s>
   The sundew trap consists of a leaf covered with sticky droplets that smell delicious.
  </s>
  <s>
   Remove old traps carefully with clean secateurs without damaging the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Their flowers aim to attract more insects and can therefore continue to bloom nicely.
  </s>
  <s>
   The growth period starts in spring to autumn (around April to around August). During this period, it is best to repot carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes - also known as tropical pitcher plants or monkey cups - have been inspiring awe in botanists since flytrap were first discovered by Europeans in the 17th century.
  </s>
  <s>
   With their dazzling colours and elaborately decorative traps, the pitcher plants seem to flaunt their carnivory with pride.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most tropical pitcher plants grow in the upper canopy of the rainforest and prefer very bright light, but without much direct sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   For highlanders, this means warm days and cool nights, e.g. 20-25°C (68-77°F) during the day and 10-15°C (50-59°F) at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   For lowlanders, you’ll need hot days and warm nights, e.g. closer to 30°C (86°F) days and 20°C (68°F) nights.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cold snaps can be lethal.
  </s>
  <s>
   One very important thing to note is that hybrids are generally far more temperature-tolerant than pure species.
  </s>
  <s>
   A lack of inflating pitchers on your plant can be a sign of insufficient humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many growing guides suggest that 80-90% humidity is optimal, but I’ve found that keeping the air so close to saturation can lead to issues with mould and fungus, particularly with low airflow.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you are successful in cultivating these plants, space can quickly become a problem.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most Nepenthes are climbing or scrambling vines, and when pitcher reach maturity some species can put out nearly a meter of stem per year!
  </s>
  <s>
   Collecting and breeding tropical pitcher plants can easily become an addiction!
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ventricosa x lowii is also known as N. x briggsiana, and this hybrid is a fast grower with red, woody pitchers and an attractively striped peristome.It's a great alternative to the more common N. x ventrata.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ventricosa X lowii has small, tubby, scarlet pitchers on glossy green leaves, and can grow into a very bushy plant!
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ‘Gaya’ is a vigorous grower with red and yellow speckled pitchers, this cultivar is N. khasiana x (ventricosa x maxima).
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes attenboroughii pitcher, grows in a mix of peat, perlite, and kanuma.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical pitcher plants benefit from frequent watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   Whereas North American pitcher plants (Sarracenia) will quickly deteriorate if given hard water from the tap, tropical pitcher plants do not seem to mind as much.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not overfeed, or your plant’s pitchers may turn black and rot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical pitcher plants are native to equatorial regions that have fairly stable conditions year-round.
  </s>
  <s>
   Fifteen years in the making and the result of more than two hundred research expeditions, Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants is a three volume work that documents all 192 currently recognised species of Nepenthes for the first time.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants is specifically designed to complement Stewart McPherson’s past books: New Nepenthes Volume 1 and New Nepenthes Volume 2.
  </s>
 </pitcher>
 <fertilizer synset="fertilizer.n.01">
  <s>
   Be cautious with fertilizers that have not been carefully tested on carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most fertilizers are too strong for these plants and may severely damage or even kill fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use fertilizers that have been recommended by experts who have tested fertilizer first.We have found MaxSea fertilizer to be the most gentle and effective.
  </s>
  <s>
   Add a pellet of Osmocote slow release fertilizer (14-14-14) to pitcher plants; Sarracenia, Cephalotus, Helimaphora and Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sometimes Osmocote pellets do lightly burn the sides of the pitchers where they come to rest inside of the pitchers, but this is not harmful long term and often can be avoided if a bit of distilled water is added at the same time as the pellet. We use Schultz cactus fertilizer on the Pinguicula, applying to the leaves only and following the instructions on the packaging for dilution.
  </s>
  <s>
   Unfortunately and ironically, carnivorous plants may be afflicted with almost all of the same pests as normal plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Our plants can be damaged by some pesticides and many are very toxic, but we have a few things that we know are safe for the plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   The constant sap sucking of aphids will cause the new leaves of sundews and pitcher plants to twist and contort as fertilizer grow.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be careful and do not use Miracle-Gro brand peat and perlite as it has been fortified with fertilizers and will harm carnivorous plants!
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend using washed horticultural sand from a local garden store.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you cannot find sand, you can often find large lava rock in a hardware or garden center with other decorative rocks.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be sure to wet perlite before use as you do not want to inhale the dust from perlite.
  </s>
  <s>
   For Temperate Pinguicula species use a Peat and Perlite mix.
  </s>
  <s>
   Apply MaxSea fertilizer once per month to the foliage and into the pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cephalotus thrive in a mix if two parts sand and/or perlite to one part peat. MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves and pitchers of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Osmocote slow release fertilizer pellets can be added to pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers add dolomite or gypsum to soil mixes, although we have not found it necessary.
  </s>
  <s>
   When it's handy, add an additional part of lava rock or pumice.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use Schultz cactus fertilizer on our Mexican and Tropical Pinguicula, applying to the leaves only and following the instructions on the packaging for dilution.
  </s>
  <s>
   MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves of the dewy pine plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Osmocote 16-16-16 fertilizer pellets are a wonderful addition to your fertilizer routine.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you would like to feed the traps of your flytrap it is recommended that you use live prey as the traps usually require continued movement from fertilizer's food to stimulate the full absorption process. They will often open too soon if fertilizer are fed inert foods and will not absorb nutrients.
  </s>
  <s>
   So-called intermediates sit somewhere in-between, while hybrids depend on the preference of the parent species.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you can’t provide sufficiently cool nights, your best bet is to try a hybrid or a tolerant intermediate.
  </s>
  <s>
   As with all carnivorous plants, remember that food and fertiliser should be near the end of your priority list!
  </s>
  <s>
   No fertiliser is better than too much.
  </s>
 </fertilizer>
 <sphagnum synset="sphagnum.n.01">
  <s>
   Each species requires its own specific blend but most carnivorous plants should be grown in some mix of peat moss, perlite, long fibered New Zealand sphagnum moss or sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you can't find horticultural sand you can use the sand used for children's sand boxes, called play sand. We use New Zealand long-fibered Sphagnum moss as a base for many of our other plants such as Nepenthes and Heliamphora.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many retail garden centers and nurseries unwittingly sell Oregon green moss as Sphagnum moss. They are not the same, in fact Oregon green moss will kill our plants if it is used.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use domestic long-fibered sphagnum to line the bottoms of our pots to prevent the peat and perlite from seeping out. Perlite can be found in many hardware stores and specialty nurseries.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use a mix of three parts New Zealand long-fibered Sphagnum moss to one part of the coarse materials, perlite, orchid bark and pumice.
  </s>
  <s>
   For a Drosophyllum mix you can use a mix composed of equal parts perlite, pumice, peat moss, and sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   The best mix for Darlingtonia Cobra plants is three parts New Zealand long-fibered sphagnum moss to one part pumice or lava rock.
  </s>
  <s>
   For Heliamphora use a mix comprised of mostly New Zealand long-fibered sphagnum moss with some pumice or lava rock mixed in.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown in live sphagnum, but take care that it doesn't overwhelm the Heliamphora.
  </s>
  <s>
   Even the live sphagnum thrives with MaxSea!
  </s>
  <s>
   The moss retains water easily and translocates nutrients effortlessly for timely release to the plant without accumulating unwanted soluble salts; management costs decrease and plant health improves.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can also make your own compost mix with peat (maximum pH of 5), sphagnum moss, grit and perlite.
  </s>
  <s>
   Popular mixtures tend to include a combination of long-fibered sphagnum moss, orchid bark, tree fern fiber, coconut husk fiber, sand, perlite, and pumice rock in varying ratios.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many growers successfully grow sphagnum's highlanders in pure long-fibered sphagnum moss.
  </s>
  <s>
   As a general rule, a mixture of long-fibered sphagnum moss, perlite, and - optionally - orchid bark works well.
  </s>
 </sphagnum>
 <soil synset="territory.n.03">
  <s>
   Unglazed terracotta pots are very porous and dry the soil out quickly.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous plants evolved to catch insects to get the fertilizers that are lacking in sundew's soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are virtually no nutrients available in soil's planting media, so carnivores need to eat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Adult fungus gnats will lay flytrap's eggs in the soil of many houseplants, including carnivorous plants. The larvae in the soil can be detrimental to the plants as they feed on roots.
  </s>
  <s>
   While deer may take an exploratory nibble of a Sarracenia, they rarely come back for seconds and overall leave the plants alone long term. Birds can be destructive of bog containers because they occasionally poke their beaks into the wet soil, looking for food like worms.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because the outdoor plants like to sit in water, raccoons can be attracted to the pots. Sometimes they will play in the water or dig out the plants. This is fairly rare and you can try sprinkling cayenne pepper on the soil to discourage them.
  </s>
  <s>
   BOTRYTIS is a fungus that often looks like fuzzy bread mold. This is a totally harmless mold, very common and even seen in the wild on the plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   On the surface of the soil of bog plants, algae slime will sometimes grow. If it is unsightly, scrape it off the surface of the soil with a spoon.
  </s>
  <s>
   Never pot sphagnum into regular garden or potting soil; this will kill sphagnum.
  </s>
  <s>
   We prefer to use a small, fine particle high quality orchid bark of 3/8-1/4 inch size.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes enjoy loose, open soil that remains wet to moist but allows drainage of excess water. They are tolerant of a wide variety of soil mixes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm temperate nepenthes varieties do well in a soil of one part peat to one part sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican and tropical nepenthes species enjoy a more open mix of equal parts sand, perlite, pumice and peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   CEPHALOTUS AND BYBLIS MIX: These will thrive in a mix if two parts sand and/or perlite to one part peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Total dissolved solids (TDS) are best if below 150 parts per million (PPM).
  </s>
  <s>
   You can purchase an inexpensive TDS meter on Amazon to test your water.
  </s>
  <s>
   When grown outdoors Sarracenia will catch plenty of food and do not need supplementation.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are 200 plus species of Bladderworts and fertilizer grow virtually worldwide, thus they come from varied climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   The terrestrial bladderworts make wonderful, miniature, flowering ground covers in the spaces around your other carnivores and can take temperatures from 40-90 degrees. Plastic containers with drainage holes work best for terrestrial and epiphytic species.
  </s>
  <s>
   When the rosettes change to flytrap's small succulents in winter, keep the soil on the dry side, dampening flytrap only slightly and occasionally.
  </s>
  <s>
   Species with larger winter leaves, like a few of the moranensis varieties or agnata, enjoy winters soils just slightly damp.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cuban species should be kept wet year-round, with only slight winter drying.
  </s>
  <s>
   Temperate Pinguicula need cold winters while soil are dormant to thrive. They do best outdoors in areas with mild winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican Butterworts do well in terrariums, greenhouses and windowsills. Mexican or Tropical butterworts have a winter dormancy that is marked by a change in the leaves from soil's carnivorous type to a tighter, more succulent leaf.
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm temperate varieties do well in a soil of one part peat to one part sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican and tropical species enjoy a more open mix of equal parts sand, perlite, vermiculite, and peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be grown easily outdoors year-round in California and the Southwest or anywhere else with hot dry summers and rainy winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Plant your dewy pine into a large terracotta clay pot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid pouring through the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   The rainbow plant does best best in tropical climates, but its annual nature allows you to grow it during any span of several months of warm weather.
  </s>
  <s>
   Rainbow plants thrive in a mix of two parts sand and one part peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   In a terrarium, high powered fluorescent light should be used and we recommend a fixture with four T-5 bulbs. Use the tray watering method, keeping the soil damp to wet year round.
  </s>
  <s>
   Keep the soil cool by watering with cold water, (refrigerated water is quite helpful on warm summer days). With the exception of the lowland form of Heliamphora heterodoxa, all Heliamphora come from high plateaus called the Tepuis, in Venezuela.
  </s>
  <s>
   If your sundew is not producing dew it most likely needs more light. Most sundews thrive on the tray method, which keeps the soil permanently wet.
  </s>
  <s>
   Winter growing species require periods of complete summer dormancy, at which time the soil has to be dried out.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes can be damaged or killed by temperatures below 50 F and in direct sun outdoors in high heat.
  </s>
  <s>
   One dormancy option is to remove the plants from seed's pots, gently clean the roots of soil, wrap the roots in a bit of damp long-fibered New Zealand sphagnum moss, place the plants in a seal-able bag and put the bag into the refrigerator. Leave soil in the refrigerator from October to February, periodically checking on soil to make sure soil are still a bit moist and are not growing any fungus.
  </s>
  <s>
   When grown outdoors Venus flytraps will catch plenty of food and do not need supplementation.
  </s>
  <s>
   Soil: General Mix Use this mix for Venus Flytraps, Sundews, and Sarracenia.
  </s>
  <s>
   Soil: Tropical Pitcher Plant Mix Use this for Nepenthes, Heliamphora, Brocchinia, and Cephalotus.
  </s>
  <s>
   All Besgrow Spagmoss is harvested from sustainable and renewable wetlands on the pristine West Coast of New Zealand’s South Island.
  </s>
  <s>
   The digestive juices are produced by glands located on that inside of the cup.
  </s>
  <s>
   Due to its carnivorous properties, Nepenthes is able to live on nutrient-poor soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   The catching cups can be low on the ground or, on the contrary, hang high in a tree.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the lowlands, it is warm both day and night.
  </s>
  <s>
   Did you know that carnivorous plants evolved in such a way that seed do not use soil as a source of nutrition, but insects? Carnivorous plants are true carnivores and eat all kinds of insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   In nature, carnivorous plants grow in swampy areas and jungles. These areas have nutrient-less soil, meaning there is no nutrition in the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous plants are used indoors as natural fly control, or outdoors in a bog garden for example.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most carnivorous plant species need a lot of water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because carnivorous plants cannot extract substances from the soil properly, it is difficult to separate the substances (which can cause roots to rot).
  </s>
  <s>
   Preferably do not use normal potting soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Flowering costs a lot of energy for a carnivorous plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Preferably use special carnivorous plant soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Their habitats are hugely diverse, and some are far more adaptable growers than others.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can monitor your humidity using a SensorPush unit, available on Amazon.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are very tolerant when it comes to soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes enjoy a loose, low-nutrition growing medium which keeps their roots aerated and allows excess water to quickly drain away while still retaining some moisture.
  </s>
  <s>
   Exactly how coarse your soil should be is dependent on numerous other factors, including ambient humidity, frequency of watering, and the species and age of your plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Certain more challenging species - including some rare highland and ultra-highland Nepenthes - often benefit from a specific mixture which reflects soil's natural habitat (e.g. whether they grow terrestrially or as an ephiphyte).
  </s>
  <s>
   Aim to keep the soil damp at all times and never let it dry out completely.
  </s>
  <s>
   Unlike many other carnivores, Nepenthes are not bog plants and do not appreciate having waterlogged soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers stand soil's pots on a layer of plastic egg crate, which helps excess water drain away.
  </s>
  <s>
   Impurities can build up over time and will often accelerate the breakdown of your soil mixture.
  </s>
 </soil>
 <veitchii>
  <s>
   Nepenthes species: Nepenthes aristolochioides, Nepenthes attenboroughii, Nepenthes edwardsiana, Nepenthes ephippiata, Nepenthes hamata, Nepenthes jamban, Nepenthes lowii, Nepenthes macrophylla, Nepenthes maxima, Nepenthes mollis, Nepenthes rajah, Nepenthes robcantleyi, Nepenthes singalana, Nepenthes veitchii, Nepenthes ventricosa
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes Hybrids: Nepenthes (lowii × veitchii) × burbidgeae, Nepenthes hamata × edwardsiana, Nepenthes rajah × (burbidgeae × edwardsiana), Nepenthes truncata × ephippiata, Nepenthes veitchii × burbidgeae, Nepenthes veitchii × lowii, Nepenthes veitchii × platychila, Dionaea
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve found N. ‘Gaya’, N. ‘Bloody Mary’, and N. x ventrata to be particularly forgiving, along with hybrids involving hairy species like N. veitchii.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can try to source smaller species such as N. glabrata, or slower growers like N. veitchii.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. veitchii is a beautiful species and one of my favourites, N. veitchii has traps with wide peristomes and is covered in fuzzy brown hair.
  </s>
 </veitchii>
 <muscipula>
  <s>
   Its Latin name Dionaea muscipula partly commemorates Venus, the goddess of beauty.
  </s>
  <s>
   Hardy carnivorous plants include Venus Flytrap (Dionaea muscipula), North American Trumpet Pitcher Plants (Sarracenia), Sundews (Drosera) and Cobra Lily (Darlingtonia), Bladderworts (Utricularia) and more.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Venus Flytrap (Dionaea muscipula) is the only plant species that can count.
  </s>
 </muscipula>
</kb>
<kb>
 <nepenthes synset="nepenthes.n.01">
  <s>
   You can use undrained containers but be prepared to water frequently.One exception to the above rule is the Dewy Pine (Drosophyllum) which prefers to be in a large terracotta pot.Mexican Pinguicula can be grown in a much more diverse range of planters.
  </s>
  <s>
   (We see this on Nepenthes as well).
  </s>
  <s>
   Exceptions are Nepenthes, Heliamphora, Cephalotus and Drosophyllum which want to be watered frequently but do not want to dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cephalotus dislike long periods of being waterlogged, so it is best to allow the water in the tray to evaporate before adding more.
  </s>
  <s>
   Plastic containers are best, but nepenthes also do well in glazed terracotta or glazed clay.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use drained containers; shallow un-drained containers will rot nepenthes's roots.
  </s>
  <s>
   TEMPERATURE: Cephalotus does best with moderately warm summers and cool to chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plants may die in long periods of very hot weather and nepenthes enjoy cool summer nights.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes require at least three hours of direct light if grown indoors on a windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you notice your plant has stopped making pitchers, it is often a sign that the plant needs a bit more light.WATER:  In greenhouses avoid the tray method of watering entirely and place the containers on benches or hang nepenthes so water can freely drain away.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes do not require any dormancy period.Lowlanders come from low elevations in tropical Southeast Asia.
  </s>
  <s>
   Darlingtonia An enigmatic plant native to Oregon and California.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes Native to SE Asia, these plants come in many shapes and sizes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Get Supplies   (view all)                  Plastic Pots 3-inch to 6-inch, including hanging pots for Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most of the 170+ Nepenthes species are found in Southeast Asia - particularly Borneo, Sumatra, and the Philippines - and the genus ranges from highland montane plants to those inhabiting steamy lowland jungles.
  </s>
  <s>
   But nepenthes's cross-fertile nature has resulted in countless unique hybrids, both in cultivation and in the wild.
  </s>
  <s>
   This guide aims to help growers of Nepenthes estimate the requirements of specific plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   These include male &amp; female parentage (remember that Nepenthes are dioecious!)
  </s>
  <s>
   Visit www.californiacarnivores.com and get 10% off by using code tomscarnivores.
  </s>
  <s>
   Visit sphagnum.co.uk and get 10% off by using code TOMS10%.
  </s>
  <s>
   They offer a nice selection of Nepenthes suitable for beginners, as well as growing supplies like compost and pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   They offer a fantastic range of Nepenthes species and hybrids suitable for growers of all abilities.
  </s>
  <s>
   Its chapters on Nepenthes are detailed and accessible and include some brilliant photography.
  </s>
  <s>
   Identify my Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you’re not sure what species you’ve got, you could try putting it into my Nepenthes Species Identifier.
  </s>
  <s>
   Top photo: Nepenthes villosa, by Brad Wilson.
  </s>
  <s>
   Me up a ladder, pollinating Nepenthes in my greenhouse!
  </s>
  <s>
   Do you grow Nepenthes?
  </s>
  <s>
   The genus has the only species known to have devoured whole rats!
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes usually grow as climbing or scrambling vines.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most species are found in Southeast Asia, nepenthes's center of distribution being the island of Borneo.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are not typically jungle plants, but prefer more open and sunny ridges, slopes and stunted forests.
  </s>
  <s>
   Seventy percent of Nepenthes are tropical highland or mountain plants, growing at elevations of 3,000 to 10,000 feet above sea level.
  </s>
  <s>
   For more information on how to grow these plants check out our Nepenthes growing tips.
  </s>
  <s>
   Highland Nepenthes    Lowland Nepenthes
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes The Monkey Cup plant (Nepenthes) belongs to the Nepenthaceae family and is a tropical plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Nepenthes got its name from its unique appearance and large ‘cups’.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because Nepenthes eats insects, it is a carnivorous plant species.
  </s>
  <s>
   At the bottom of the cup of the Nepenthes is a viscous liquid full of digestive juices (enzymes).
  </s>
  <s>
   Some cups of nepenthes species can grow up to 50cm tall!
  </s>
  <s>
   The Nepenthes can be found in different parts of the world and is mostly found in Southeast Asia (Borneo).
  </s>
  <s>
   In addition, the plant species can be found in Sri Lanka, Madagascar and Seychelles.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most Nepenthes grow in tropical slope forests.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are also Nepenthes plants that can be found at altitudes of up to 3,000 metres.
  </s>
  <s>
   These are ‘highland’ Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   A climbing Nepenthes in nature can grow up to 15 metres tall.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes likes sun very much.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Nepenthes plant can also grow beautiful yellow / brown flowers in the form of clusters.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant has successfully caught the insect and the insect won’t break free from it.The ‘Cup’ trap:This trap is used by Nepenthes (Monkey Cup plant), amongst others.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes is found in Jungles all over the world.
  </s>
  <s>
   Ranging in size from diminutive miniatures like Nepenthes argentii to gargantuan monstrosities like Nepenthes rajah, the genus includes the only carnivorous plants known to have caught and eaten whole rats.
  </s>
  <s>
   The genus is hugely diverse, and some species have stricter temperature requirements than others.
  </s>
  <s>
   Even so, most cultivation advice is broadly applicable to all Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Follow this guide and soon you'll need to prune your Nepenthes to keep it in check!
  </s>
  <s>
   Growing Locations There are over 170 species of Nepenthes, plus countless natural and cultivated hybrids.
  </s>
  <s>
   High-powered fluorescent or LED lights (such as T5 growlights) work very well with Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve found that LEDs growlights can be particularly effective since nepenthes tend to give off less heat than fluorescent bulbs.
  </s>
  <s>
   A Nepenthes terrarium with a T5 grow light, built by me many years ago.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes maxima thriving in my terrarium.
  </s>
  <s>
   Note that Nepenthes do not require a winter dormancy, but if you’re growing under natural light, the shorter daylight hours will often slow your plant down significantly.
  </s>
  <s>
   Temperature Each Nepenthes species grows best at the temperatures it experiences in its natural habitat.
  </s>
  <s>
   These temperatures correspond to the altitudes at which nepenthes grow in the wild.
  </s>
  <s>
   Remember that Nepenthes are tropical montane plants, and so most require some kind of temperature drop at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes villosa, grown by Simon Lumb, an example of a true highlander.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes bicalarata at Chester Zoo, an example of a true lowlander.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many Nepenthes hybrids are particularly tolerant of lower humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are quite adaptable to lower levels, as long as the growing media is kept moist.
  </s>
  <s>
   Space When you first start growing Nepenthes, space probably won’t be at the top of your list.
  </s>
  <s>
   Small plants often grow slowly and may take a while to adapt to the conditions of nepenthes's new home.
  </s>
  <s>
   Remember that Nepenthes can get very large and will produce climbing vines - these will need to be pruned!
  </s>
  <s>
   Greenhouses: A greenhouse heated to a minimum of 12°C and covered with shade cloth is undoubtedly the best way to grow a wide variety of highland Nepenthes species on a large scale - you can read about my own greenhouse setup here.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers create warm chambers within nepenthes's greenhouses for lowlanders.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes ephippiata, one of my favourite species, thriving in my greenhouse.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes edwardsiana, another favourite.
  </s>
  <s>
   Species and Hybrids There are over 170 known species of Nepenthes, and more are described each year.
  </s>
  <s>
   What’s more, all of nepenthes are cross-fertile with one another to at least some degree.
  </s>
  <s>
   Note that Nepenthes hybrids are often easier growers than pure species plants (on account of so-called ‘hybrid vigour’).
  </s>
  <s>
   For now, I’ll recommend some easy-to-grow hybrids and species:    Nepenthes x ventrata.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes 'Bloody Mary'.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes 'Gaya'.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve written a detailed profile of Nepenthes maxima.
  </s>
  <s>
   They offer a nice selection of Nepenthes suitable for beginners, including many of the cultivars recommended above.
  </s>
  <s>
   For example, I’ve found Nepenthes rajah and Nepenthes attenboroughii to benefit from a more ultramafic substrate - mine grow well in a mixture of peat moss, perlite, and kanuma.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the UK, South West Carnivorous Plants offers both a ready-made Nepenthes compost, and components for mixing your own (e.g.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes are more tolerant of water impurities and dissolved minerals than other carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   My recommended foods for Venus flytraps will all work, but dried crickets are particularly suitable for Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   For experienced growers with larger collections, you could also try Osmocote Flower and Vegetable pellets - I tried these following a recommendation from Peter D’Amato, and my plants seemed to enjoy nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   In my experience, though, the most effective food for Nepenthes is a water-soluble seaweed-based fertiliser, mixed in a spray bottle and squirted into the pitchers every few weeks.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes rajah x (burbidgeae x edwardsiana).
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes robcantleyi.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes truncata x ephippiata, known to catch mice!
  </s>
  <s>
   Unlike many other carnivores, Nepenthes can also benefit from foliar fertilisation.
  </s>
  <s>
   When grown in the northern hemisphere, Nepenthes don’t always flower on a regular schedule like plants native to temperate climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   It varies by species, but in my experience many mature Nepenthes grown under natural light will flower in the Autumn.
  </s>
  <s>
   You’ll know when a Nepenthes is about to flower when it produces an infloresence before its next leaf.
  </s>
  <s>
   A female Nepenthes inflorescence.
  </s>
  <s>
   Female Nepenthes flowers opening.
  </s>
  <s>
   Female Nepenthes flowers swelling, some time after being pollinated.
  </s>
  <s>
   Flowers on a male Nepenthes producing yellow pollen.
  </s>
  <s>
   One of the many fascinating things about Nepenthes is that nepenthes are dioecious, meaning all individual plants are either male or female!
  </s>
  <s>
   This is extremely unusual among plants, which normally have both male and female reproductive parts in nepenthes's flowers (pollen from anthers, and a female stigma).
  </s>
  <s>
   Its chapters on Nepenthes are detailed and accessible and include some brilliant photography.
  </s>
  <s>
   Identify your Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you’re not sure what species you’ve got, you could try putting it into the Nepenthes Species Identifier.
  </s>
  <s>
   Top photo: Nepenthes madagascariensis, by Tom Ballinger.
  </s>
  <s>
   The New Nepenthes series includes countless expedition reports, conservation assessments and wild observations that underpin the treatment and taxonomy presented here.
  </s>
  <s>
   This paper, titled Delimitation of the Nepenthes macfarlanei Group with Two Species Described as New by Gideon Lim, Michal R. Golos, François Sockhom Mey, Andreas Wistuba, Stewart R. McPherson and Alastair S. Robinson can be downloaded totally free of charge via the following link:  DOWNLOAD DELIMITATION OF THE NEPENTHES MACFARLANEI GROUP PDF  Video        Dustjacket            Sample Pages                                                                                                                                                                                  MenuBooks Ideas Submission Bespoke Publishing Service About Documentaries Expeditions Terms, Conditions and FAQs Contact Stay in touch with everything Redfern and follow us on social media.
  </s>
 </nepenthes>
 <sarracenia synset="sarracenia.n.01">
  <s>
   Organic does not mean non-toxic.MEALYBUGS: This can look like cotton fluff in the growth points of your Sarracenia or at the base of Nepenthes leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   First, clean off any old growth; trim leaves back, remove old scales of leaves at the rhizome of Sarracenia and cut back any dying or dead growth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Follow the directions on the package for application.POWDERY MILDEW: This is similar looking to botrytis but is not as fluffy and is very common on Sarracenia.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sulphur is the best treatment for powdery, follow directions on the packaging for application.SOOTY MOLD: Commonly seen on Sarracenia this looks just like it sounds; like a black mold all over the pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sometimes the lids of Sarracenia will slightly burn, this is the sweet nectar burning a bit in the hot sun, it is totally normal and nothing to worry about.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you live in a very hot, dry and sunny area, like Arizona, it will be best to grow sarracenia in full morning sun with protection from the afternoon sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   WATER: Always keep sarracenia sitting in a saucer with a few inches of distilled or purified water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not let sarracenia dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   It exists on all Sarracenia but is more noticeable on the anthocyanin-free plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Temperate sundews require cold winters see the dormancy instructions for Sarracenia.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sarracenia Coming soon!
  </s>
 </sarracenia>
 <drosera synset="drosera.n.01">
  <s>
   You can use MaxSea on Nepenthes, Drosera, Venus Flytraps, Sarracenia, Darlintonia, Heliamphora, Cephalotus and Drosophyllum.Use caution and lower concentrations when fertilizing more finicky South African sundews like Drosera regia, glabripes and slackii.
  </s>
  <s>
   Often, Pinguicula and Drosera will catch many of these adults and help reduce the population.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sundews  (Drosera)                                    SUN: Full to part sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   Drosera Coming soon!
  </s>
 </drosera>
 <flytrap synset="flytrap.n.01">
  <s>
   This can be applied twice a month.To feed Venus flytrap traps, use live mealworms (usually available at pet stores) or other live bugs.
  </s>
  <s>
   Use a pair of tongs or tweezers to feed the insect or worm to the trap, triggering the trigger hairs to cause the trap to close.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant can be triggered to close but often the trap will reopen in a day or two, which indicates that it has not completed digestion.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid contact with skin and eyes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid contact with skin and eyes.
  </s>
  <s>
   THRIPS: Sarracenia are a favorite of thrips; flytrap's chewing causes silvery patches on the pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid contact with skin and eyes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dogs are easily dissuaded when pots are relocated to high spots.
  </s>
  <s>
   This can be easily broken up with a hammer.
  </s>
  <s>
   The water vending machines at your local grocery store are a good, inexpensive source for pure water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Brita and Pur water filters, however, do not remove enough dissolved salts to make much difference.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is good to routinely check the TDS of this water source as these levels can fluctuate with the seasonal droughts.Most carnivorous plants love being in water!
  </s>
  <s>
   This is especially important on the hottest days, be sure to check your water levels frequently in the summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use distilled, reverse osmosis or rain water only.TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY: These are warm-temperate plants meaning that flytrap need warm summers and chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be grown in terrariums under bright fluorescent light, we recommend a fixture with four T5 bulbs or LEDs.
  </s>
  <s>
   Use chilly water for your temperate pings.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Mexican varieties can be kept on the tray system with overhead watering while flytrap have carnivorous foliage in summer and autumn.
  </s>
  <s>
   Best in light-colored, preferably white, plastic or glazed ceramic pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   Single plants grow well in six- to eight-inch pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   Then reduce watering so that it slowly goes dry over the course of a month.
  </s>
  <s>
   Keep in a cool, dry place during summer dormancy and sprinkle flytrap with water once every couple of weeks.TEMPERATURE: As sundews grow worldwide, flytrap come from varied climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many can be grown easily on a sunny windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrariums with high-powered fluorescent lights are easy to set up and ideal; we recommend four T-5 lights.
  </s>
  <s>
   In terrariums and on windowsills, place the pot in a shallow saucer and water overhead as soon as the water in the saucer evaporates.
  </s>
  <s>
   Don't allow the pot to sit in deep water for extended periods of time as this can lead to root rot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Constant temperatures in 80's F with high humidity is ideal, although some species will grow on sunny windowsills in warm homes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most highlanders can be easily grown on sunny windowsills.
  </s>
  <s>
   For instance, we recommend against using terracotta or un-glazed ceramic for most carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   While some species may adapt to life on a windowsill, most prefer a greenhouse or terrarium.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are known for flytrap's showy, large, orchid-like flowers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grow Outdoor Perennials   (view all)                  Venus Flytrap An American Classic!
  </s>
  <s>
   Native to North Carolina, the Venus Flytrap    likes full sun during summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grow on a sunny windowsill with    partial to dappled sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   Can take full sun, so grow it in the sunniest window in your home.
  </s>
  <s>
   I got my first Venus flytrap at age 10 and now have an entire greenhouse full of carnivores.
  </s>
  <s>
   As with all plants, the key to successfully growing Nepenthes in cultivation is the ability to replicate the conditions of flytrap's natural habitat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Heads up!
  </s>
  <s>
   Available on the Redfern website.
  </s>
  <s>
   Anatomy of a Potted Venus Flytrap
  </s>
  <s>
   31 Jul 2022 - Pinned If you've just returned from the garden centre with your first flytrap, or are looking for an easy-to-grow carnivorous plant as a unusual gift, this is for you!
  </s>
  <s>
   21 May 2023 If you've spotted a long stem emerging from your flytrap, what should you do with it?
  </s>
  <s>
   Will cutting it off encourage your flytrap to grow more vigorously?
  </s>
  <s>
   31 Jul 2022 - Pinned If you've just returned from the garden centre with your first flytrap, or are looking for an easy-to-grow carnivorous plant as a unusual gift, this is for you!
  </s>
  <s>
   21 May 2023 If you've spotted a long stem emerging from your flytrap, what should you do with it?
  </s>
  <s>
   Will cutting it off encourage your flytrap to grow more vigorously?
  </s>
  <s>
   Megan will demonstrate how to build an attractive, low-maintenance display of hardy carnivorous plants that can be kept indoors or outside.
  </s>
  <s>
   12 Jun 2022 If your flytrap's leaves are turning black, don't panic - traps can die for many different reasons and this is rarely fatal to the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve been growing carnivorous plants for over 2 decades, having been fascinated by these plants since I got my first Venus flytrap at age 10.
  </s>
  <s>
   I now have a large greenhouse to house my personal collection.
  </s>
  <s>
   How can I contact you?
  </s>
  <s>
   Struggling with your flytrap?
  </s>
  <s>
   Besgrow Spagmoss has naturally low concentrations of soluble salts, is virtually sterile and can hold up to 20 times its weight in water.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant can be kept in both a hanging pot and an upright pot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Product range.
  </s>
  <s>
   In every shape and size, and each species has a different appearance and a different lure method.
  </s>
  <s>
   Below you will find a quick overview of the various type of traps.The ‘Clap’ trapThis trap is used by the best-known carnivorous plant, the Venus Flytrap.
  </s>
  <s>
   In this mouth there are three to nine hairs.
  </s>
  <s>
   When an insect lands in this trap and touches one of these hairs – twice – within 20 seconds, the trap closes.
  </s>
  <s>
   This trap resembles a trumpet.
  </s>
  <s>
   Once the insect lands on the trap, it sticks to it.
  </s>
  <s>
   Old traps are best to be removed.
  </s>
  <s>
   As a result, the traps will not grow quickly.
  </s>
  <s>
   For this reason, it is best to remove the flowers if traps don’t develop as flytrap should (unless, of course, you find the flowers extra beautiful).
  </s>
  <s>
   I got my first Venus flytrap at age 10 and now have an entire greenhouse full of carnivores.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the northern hemisphere that could be an east or west-facing window which receives direct sun for only part of the day, or a greenhouse with 50% shade cloth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Too much direct sun can burn flytrap's leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many of these will grow quite happily on a cool windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grow Tents: Providing you can maintain good humidity levels and avoid your lights overheating the interior of the tent, these can be a great way to grow a variety of species and hybrids.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you wish to grow highland and ultra-highland species but struggle to provide the necessary low temperatures, some enthusiasts have success cooling flytrap's tents at night with specially-adapted freezers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use pots with plenty of drainage holes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sold as a set of three volumes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Available as standard hardback books and limited edition, premium leather-bound, collector’s edition volumes!
  </s>
 </flytrap>
 <utricularia synset="utricularia.n.01">
  <s>
   When the Pinguicula has formed these tight, succulent leaves you can withhold water as described above for the dormancy period.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical Bladderworts (Utricularia)  Tropical Bladderworts (Utricularia) are all from the Caribbean, Central America, and South America.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrestrial Bladderworts (Utricularia)  Terrestrial Bladderworts (Utricularia) are easy to grow and produce profusions of flowers.
  </s>
  <s>
   The flowers of the Pinguicula are an exception to this.
  </s>
 </utricularia>
 <seed synset="seeded_player.n.01">
  <s>
   It is organic and has almost no odor.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to treat the plant at least twice, 1 week apart.
  </s>
  <s>
   Continue until seed're all gone.
  </s>
  <s>
   Lastly, we recommend spraying your plants with Sevin.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to treat the plant at least twice, 1 week apart.
  </s>
  <s>
   Continue until seed're all gone.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend treating with Monterey Garden Spray, the main ingredient is Spinosad.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to treat the plant at least twice, 1 week apart.
  </s>
  <s>
   Continue until seed're all gone.
  </s>
  <s>
   Then you will have to spray.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is organic and has almost no odor.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to treat the plant at least twice, 1 week apart.
  </s>
  <s>
   Continue until seed're all gone.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mosquito BTs are a safe and effective way to treat these.
  </s>
  <s>
   This looks like a tiny green jell-o mold.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is non-harmful and no treatment is needed.
  </s>
  <s>
   Another good mix is two parts lava rock, and or pumice to one part peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you do have hard water, it is best to use collected rain water, distilled water, reverse osmosis water, or de-ionized water.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is really the best and easiest way to make sure your plants don't ever dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is common for several of the traps to "burn" and die back when you first put it into the sun, it is just getting used to the full sun exposure and it will quickly grow new traps.
  </s>
  <s>
   They thrive in temperatures ranging from 20 degrees - 90 F degrees and can take a freeze or high temperature spike up to 110 F degrees for a brief period.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you live in an area with very cold winters, where night time temperatures drop below 20 degrees for sustained periods, you have options for providing seed with a winter dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dormancy is triggered by a combination of exposure to shorter photo periods and cooler temperatures in the 50-60's F.  While you can skip a dormancy period once or twice, long term your plant will begin to do poorly and will eventually die if you skip this crucial period.Your can bring your plant indoors to a sunny windowsill in an unheated room or garage where the night time temperatures will dip down into the 50-60 F.  Leave it sitting in water during this period and put it outside again when outside temperatures increase.
  </s>
  <s>
   Or you can mulch seed in very, very well outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to pack at least four inches of mulch on top of the plants and all around the sides to prevent winds from chilling seed.
  </s>
  <s>
   It can be difficult to wipe off, but the more persnickety of us can try!
  </s>
  <s>
   Our tropical species do best in warm greenhouses and terrariums.
  </s>
  <s>
   The warm temperate species from the U.S. tolerate light frost and brief freezes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cooler nights are ideal.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown on cool, sunny windowsills sometimes, but the best plants are grown in climate controlled greenhouses or terrariums where day temps remain in the 70's F and night time temps in the 40's to 50's F.Because of seed's need for temperature control we recommend specific containers.
  </s>
  <s>
   A few prefer to be waterlogged.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are not tolerant of low temperatures.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is common for several of the traps to "burn" and die back when you first put it into the sun, it is just getting used to the full sun exposure and it will quickly grow new traps.
  </s>
  <s>
   They thrive in temperatures ranging from 20 degrees - 90 F degrees and can take a freeze or high temperature spike up to 100 F degrees for a brief period.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you live in an area with very cold winters, where night time temperatures drop below 20 degrees for sustained periods, you have three options for providing seed with a winter dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dormancy is triggered by a combination of exposure to shorter photo periods and cooler temperatures in the 50-60's F.  While you can skip a dormancy period once or twice, long term your plant will begin to do poorly and will eventually die if you skip this crucial period.Your first option is to bring your plant indoors to a sunny windowsill in an unheated room or garage where the night time temperatures will dip down into the 50-60 F.  Leave it sitting in water during this period and put it outside again when outside temperatures increase.
  </s>
  <s>
   The second option is to mulch seed in very, very well outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to pack at least four inches of mulch on top of the plants and all around the sides to prevent winds from chilling seed.
  </s>
  <s>
   Meticulously Packaged   Your plants will arrive as if you came here and pick  up yourself!
  </s>
  <s>
   Partial to dappled sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   Happy growing!
  </s>
  <s>
   and whether either of the parent species is particularly challenging to grow.
  </s>
  <s>
   Still want to learn more?
  </s>
  <s>
   In my opinion, this is the best introduction to carnivorous plants you can buy.
  </s>
  <s>
   This monograph by Stewart McPherson is essential reading for anyone with a serious interest in the genus.
  </s>
  <s>
   Happy growing!
  </s>
  <s>
   It is common for several of the traps to "burn" and die back when you first put it into the sun, it is just getting used to the full sun exposure and it will quickly grow new traps.
  </s>
  <s>
   They thrive in temperatures ranging from 20 degrees - 90 F degrees and can take a freeze or high temperature spike up to 100 F degrees for a brief period.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you live in an area with very cold winters, where night time temperatures drop below 20 degrees for sustained periods, you have three options for providing seed with a winter dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dormancy is triggered by a combination of exposure to shorter photo periods and cooler temperatures in the 50-60's F. While you can skip a dormancy period once or twice, long term your plant will begin to do poorly and will eventually die if you skip this crucial period.Your first option is to bring your plant indoors to a sunny windowsill in an unheated room or garage where the night time temperatures will dip down into the 50-60 F. Leave it sitting in water during this period and put it outside again when outside temperatures increase.
  </s>
  <s>
   The second option is to mulch seed in very, very well outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   You will need to pack at least four inches of mulch on top of the plants and all around the sides to prevent winds from chilling seed.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can navigate using      the categories above, or browse my most popular resources below.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some of these can get really large - but which is the biggest?
  </s>
  <s>
   8 Oct 2022 Most carnivorous plants - including Venus flytraps - are native to temperate climates, and seed survive the winters by entering a resting phase.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some of these can get really large - but which is the biggest?
  </s>
  <s>
   8 Oct 2022 Most carnivorous plants - including Venus flytraps - are native to temperate climates, and seed survive the winters by entering a resting phase.
  </s>
  <s>
   Species that grow below 3,000 feet are considered lowland.
  </s>
  <s>
   Inside the cup itself are sturdy hairs that are pointed downwards.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous PlantsAre you looking for an exciting and fascinating plant?
  </s>
  <s>
   Then a carnivorous plant might be something for you!
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not give carnivorous plants tap water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some carnivorous plants grow flowers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Here we tell you more about carnivorous plants and your most frequently asked questions.
  </s>
  <s>
   Please feel free to contact us.
  </s>
  <s>
   We are happy to help you.Buy Carnivorous PlantsWould you like to buy your own carnivorous plant?
  </s>
  <s>
   For this reason, it’s difficult to offer generalised advice on growing locations which is applicable to all species!
  </s>
  <s>
   Diffused or partial sun is ideal.
  </s>
  <s>
   These tend to be the showiest species.
  </s>
  <s>
   In my experience, it’s also possible for humidity to be too high!
  </s>
  <s>
   This is worth bearing in mind if you opt for a terrarium or other enclosed space.
  </s>
  <s>
   Either way, you may soon find yourself having to aggressively prune your plants!
  </s>
  <s>
   Your Options!
  </s>
  <s>
   Windowsills: Some easy-to-grow species and cultivars (see below for suggestions) can adapt to the lower humidity of a bright windowsill, providing seed's other requirements are met.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrariums: Paired with T5 growlights, a large terrarium can be a great way to grow young plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Back to top.
  </s>
  <s>
   As a result there are many thousands of unique hybrids in cultivation, from simple primary hybrids to extraordinarily complex mixtures of dozens of species.
  </s>
  <s>
   As such, don’t limit yourself to just species when looking to start your collection - in fact, starting with hybrids is often a good choice.
  </s>
  <s>
   For UK growers, I highly recommend South West Carnivorous Plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Back to top.
  </s>
  <s>
   These two also prefer being given room for extensive root growth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Back to top.
  </s>
  <s>
   For long-term healthy growth, stick to rainwater, distilled or deionised water, or water purified using a reverse-osmosis (RO) system.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve written more about water for carnivorous plants, so be sure to give that a read if you’re unsure what to do.
  </s>
  <s>
   Back to top.
  </s>
  <s>
   Food for Nepenthes If you are growing your Nepenthes where seed will not be able to catch seed's own food, dried insects can be dropped into the pitchers every few weeks.
  </s>
  <s>
   The results have been excellent, as you can see below!
  </s>
  <s>
   Back to top.
  </s>
  <s>
   Seed pods ripening on a female Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   A fully ripe Nepenthes seed pod split open and ready to harvest.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is one reason why species seed is seldom produced in cultivation - even if you are a skilled enough grower to have multiple mature specimens of the same species in flower at the same time, there’s no guarantee you’ll have a male and a female.
  </s>
  <s>
   Soon I’ll write a separate guide to producing Nepenthes seed, as well as propagating via other methods such as cuttings.
  </s>
  <s>
   Back to top.
  </s>
  <s>
   Still want to learn more?
  </s>
  <s>
   In my opinion, this is the best introduction to carnivorous plants you can buy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Discover all 170+ species.
  </s>
  <s>
   Happy growing!
  </s>
  <s>
   You’ll love it too.
  </s>
 </seed>
 <care synset="care.n.04">
  <s>
   Care Guides                No terrariums.
  </s>
  <s>
   Help Center                                 FAQ                                                  GENERAL GROWING AND CARE                                                                          CONTAINERS                                    Plastic or glazed ceramic pots are best for most carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Live prey will stimulate the trap to close tightly, seal and emit the digestive fluids needed to break down the insect.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can use a cotton swab dipped in medicinal alcohol (the kind used in first aid kits) to swab in between leaves on the rhizome, or any other nooks and crannies where you see evidence of mealy bug.
  </s>
  <s>
   Repeat application in 7 days.
  </s>
  <s>
   This fungus loves fresh new growth in particular.
  </s>
  <s>
   This can be combatted with increased light, better airflow and reducing overhead watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   Luckily the plants are non-toxic to our beloved pets.
  </s>
  <s>
   Depending on the persistence of your cat you may need to relocate your plants to an inaccessbile shelf or into a terrarium indoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   Basically the mix should be airy and the rock ingredients will help cool the roots.
  </s>
  <s>
   The mix should be airy and the rock ingredients will help keep the mix open and cool.
  </s>
  <s>
   And here is one on care.
  </s>
  <s>
   For the first 6-8 months care should be kept damp at all times.
  </s>
  <s>
   As care approach maturity, care should no longer sit in water for long periods of time.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can take light frost and brief freezes.
  </s>
  <s>
   They should be brought in or protected during long freezes below 25 F.  Ours plants take night time temps of 25 F without damage, as long as it warms back up during the day.SOIL: Unlike most carnivores, Dewy Pines need to be kept a little on the dry side.
  </s>
  <s>
   As such care require a special mix.
  </s>
  <s>
   It should be at least 12" in diameter.
  </s>
  <s>
   Rainbow Plants (Byblis)                                    SUN: Full to part sun.WATER: Use the tray method.
  </s>
  <s>
   The mix should be airy and the rock ingredients will help keep the mix open and cool.
  </s>
  <s>
   All pots must have drainage holes!
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use distilled, reverse osmosis or rain water only.
  </s>
  <s>
   These plants are especially sensitive to care's water quality and it is very important to give care mineral and salt free water.TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY: These are warm-temperate plants meaning that care need warm summers and chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend live meal worms available from any pet store.For even more info: Venus Flytrap Care (californiacarnivores.com)                       Copy to clipboard
  </s>
  <s>
   After-Purchase Support   If you need help with your plants, we're here for you!
  </s>
  <s>
   You’ll also get better advice on successful cultivation, and you’ll be supporting a small business!
  </s>
  <s>
   His beautiful hardbacks include photography and detailed descriptions of all known species.
  </s>
  <s>
   Venus Flytrap Care Charles Darwin called the Venus flytrap “the most wonderful plant in the world”.
  </s>
  <s>
   These strange and wonderful plants are easy and rewarding to grow, and we've put together all the information you need to care for yours in one place.
  </s>
  <s>
   VIDEO GUIDES        VENUS FLYTRAP CARE (TEXT) SUN: Full sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use distilled, reverse osmosis or rain water only.
  </s>
  <s>
   These plants are especially sensitive to care's water quality and it is very important to give care mineral and salt free water.TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY: These are warm-temperate plants meaning that care need warm summers and chilly winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Each profile includes botanical history, growing tips, photos, conservation      status, availability, and more.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is a common problem, and one which is easy to diagnose and fix.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is called dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is a common problem, and one which is easy to diagnose and fix.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is called dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Whether you’re a long-time greenhouse grower or simply curious about carnivorous plants, Tom’s Carnivores has something for you.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tom’s Carnivores is my attempt to create a valuable resource for today’s growers.
  </s>
  <s>
   In 2023 following the birth of my second child, it became too difficult to keep up with demand.
  </s>
  <s>
   Visit californiacarnivores.com and get 10% off with code tomscarnivores.
  </s>
  <s>
   They experience hot days, warm nights, and continuous high humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Above the lowland heat of the rainforest, the mountain climate can be considerably cooler and wetter, especially at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the orchid growing industry, it is renowned for having long, strong strands, great longevity, high rot resistance, and peerless water-holding capacity.
  </s>
  <s>
   The combination of long strands and high water-permeability ensures strong and healthy root development.
  </s>
  <s>
   Naturally Sustainable &amp; RenewableBesgrow Spagmoss is hand-picked and naturally air dried to ensure its purity and to guarantee its remarkable water holding capacity (maximum WHC of 96%).
  </s>
  <s>
   The function of the smooth edge is that an insect has no grip and therefore slides into the cup.
  </s>
  <s>
   Winners of 7 Golden Medals at RHS Chelsea Flower Show.
  </s>
  <s>
   We also offer various outdoor carnivorous plants that will thrive well in the UK.The TrapsEach species within the carnivorous plant family has a different baiting method.
  </s>
  <s>
   The fly trap manifests itself in the shape of a mouth.
  </s>
  <s>
   The cup has an attractive colour and produces an attractive smell that lures insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   This smell attracts insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   These types are ideal for controlling fruit flies.Care for Carnivorous PlantsEach carnivorous plant species needs its own care.
  </s>
  <s>
   Read more about comprehensive carnivorous plant care by species here.
  </s>
  <s>
   The general care of carnivorous plants will be described below.WaterPreferably use rainwater, osmosis water or distilled water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Read more about how much water each species needs on our general care page.
  </s>
  <s>
   Let's get started!
  </s>
  <s>
   However, the guidance below is a good starting point and can be adapted to allow you to grow a wide variety of plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   When selecting a location for your Nepenthes, there are four main things to consider:  Light Temperature Humidity Space  We’ll go through each of these in turn, then look at some common growing locations and care's associated advantages and disadvantages.
  </s>
  <s>
   Artificial light is also an option.
  </s>
  <s>
   Humidity Humidity should ideally be quite high - at least 50% relative humidity (RH) during the daytime, and higher at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers have success using a misting bottle daily to raise humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Regular light watering can help to raise humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. maxima: Red patterning on a green background with a large, flamboyant red peristome (lip).
  </s>
  <s>
   Available in many varieties (including the famous wavy-leaf form), this is an attractive plant which is particularly adaptable to warmer conditions.
  </s>
  <s>
   You should aim to take care of all your plant’s other needs (lighting, temperature, humidity, and so on) before thinking about feeding &amp; fertilisation.
  </s>
  <s>
   10 kg ORDER YOURS NOW!
  </s>
  <s>
   Introductory chapters include a detailed overview of the biogeography, ecology, remarkable adaptations and taxonomy of the genus.
  </s>
  <s>
   Each species profile includes detailed sections (written in clear and accessible language) covering morphology, diversity, ecology and conservation status.
  </s>
  <s>
   Concluding chapters comprise a thorough exploration of Nepenthes hybrids and a uniquely detailed review of the conservation status of the genus with an overview of the most imperilled taxa, the threats afflicting care and avenues for future conservation efforts.
  </s>
 </care>
 <dionaea synset="dionaea.n.01">
  <s>
   Venus Flytrap (Dionaea)                                    SUN: Full sun.
  </s>
 </dionaea>
 <sundew synset="sundew.n.01">
  <s>
   No nonsense   Get the straight facts from guys who grow and propagate thousands of carnivorus plants every year since 1995.
  </s>
  <s>
   These plants have a very shallow root system.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because of this, sundew can be grown in small, shallow planters with no drainage.
  </s>
  <s>
   We find sundew can be potted into teacups, vintage pottery, seashells, on lava rocks and other novelty planters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Check out our YouTube channel for lots of ideas on the diverse ways you can use Butterworts in your planters!
  </s>
  <s>
   MaxSea may be used from seedlings to mature specimens.
  </s>
  <s>
   Luckily all of these little plant parasites are treatable.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can spray your plants with "Take Down"; the active ingredients are canola oil and pyrethrin, which comes from a daisy relative.
  </s>
  <s>
   Make sure and cover every surface of the infected plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Next, take a hose on the jet or flat setting and spray your plant off, being very careful of the growth points and leaves as you do not want to damage your plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Make sure and cover every surface of the infected plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Make sure and cover every surface of the infected plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Make sure and cover every surface of the infected plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be careful to wet it before use as breathing in perlite dust can be harmful.PUMICE: This can be found in many hardware stores and specialty nurseriesLAVA ROCK: We use a small grade of lava rock, about the size of a pea.
  </s>
  <s>
   WATER                                    All carnivorous plants should be grown with a pure, low mineral water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Butterworts (Pinguicula)                                    SUN:  Mexican or Tropical Butterworts are great for a sunny windowsill.
  </s>
  <s>
   When grown under high intensity fluorescent grow lights many of sundew will blush so that the entire plant is glowing pink or red!
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm Temperate Butterworts do well outdoors in part sun to full sun with a bit of protection from afternoon sun.WATER: All temperate and warm temperate species should be grown permanently wet on the tray system, with frequent overhead watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can usually tell how dry a species enjoys its winter by the size of its succulent leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   We wait for the butterworts to go dormant before we stop watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   And when sundew begin growing sundew's carnivorous leaves we begin the tray method of watering again.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not worry too much about providing this dormancy; if your plants do not start to grow the succulent type leaves, which look very different than sundew's regular leaves, you do not need to withhold water.SOIL: Temperate species: Use a mix of two parts peat, one part sand, and one part perlite.
  </s>
  <s>
   Flowering plants should be kept a bit drier.TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY: These plants require no dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most species of sundew require at least six hours of direct light to thrive.
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm-temperate and sub-tropical sundews do well on windowsills, in cool greenhouses, or terrariums and appreciate cool nights.
  </s>
  <s>
   Winter growing sundews from Australia and South Africa could be grown outdoors in a Mediterranean climate without frost or in a cool greenhouse.
  </s>
  <s>
   Terrestrial bladderworts will grow happily alongside many carnivorous plants in bogs.
  </s>
  <s>
   Hardy Sundews Many are native to the United States.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grow Tropical Plants   (view all)                  Sundews A plant with dewy, sticky leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many grow well as regular houseplants with partial sunlight.
  </s>
  <s>
   At the top of the inside of Monkey cup plant’s leaf is a smooth edge.
  </s>
  <s>
   At the bottom of the trap is a watery secretion that digests and converts the prey into food.The ‘Sticky’ trap:This trap is used by Drosera (Sundew) and Pinguicula (Butterwort), among others.
  </s>
  <s>
   The lime contained in tap water is bad for carnivorous plants and can cause lime build-up in the long term.
  </s>
  <s>
   What's more, many common hybrids are extremely tolerant growers and make excellent houseplants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Spindly leaves and a lack of colouration are signs of insufficient light, while blotchy red marks can be a sign your plant is getting more than enough light.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ‘Bloody Mary’: A popular cultivar for terrariums, this is a beautiful hybrid between N. ventricosa and N. ampullaria.
  </s>
  <s>
   It’s a particularly good candidate for a houseplant.
  </s>
  <s>
   During the spring &amp; summer, spraying your plant with a weak solution of high-quality orchid fertiliser several times a month can help promote good growth.
  </s>
 </sundew>
 <pitcher synset="pitcher.n.05">
  <s>
   No myths.
  </s>
  <s>
   OUTDOOR PERENNIALS  USDA Zone Chart Darlingtonia: Cobra Plant Dionaea: Venus Flytraps Drosera: Hardy Sundews Pinguicula: Hardy Butterworts Sarracenia: American Pitcher Plants                            TROPICAL PLANTS   Cephalotus: Australian Pitcher Drosera: Tropical Sundews Heliamphora: Sun Pitchers Nepenthes: Asian Pitchers Pinguicula: Mexican Butterworts                           GERMINATING SEEDS  Venus Flytrap Seeds Hardy Sundews and Sarracenia Seeds Tropical Sundew Seeds
  </s>
  <s>
   We prefer small plastic pots with holes in the bottom, so that the tray method may be used.
  </s>
  <s>
   Healthy plants that have access to lots of prey don't necessarily need any fertilizing, although it would still be beneficial.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pour into the pitchers of all pitcher plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Put one pellet into each pitcher.
  </s>
  <s>
   Feeding a dead insect or inert food, such as hamburger, is less likely to trigger the full digestive process of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   It will stay closed for many days to complete the full digestion process.
  </s>
  <s>
   The plant needs the live prey to stimulate this full process or it will reopen, thinking it has caught an inert and indigestible item.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid contact with skin and eyes.SCALE: Scale look like little waxy scabs that encrust the leaves and stems.
  </s>
  <s>
   Scale may be wiped away with rubbing alcohol on a Q-tip or cotton pad.
  </s>
  <s>
   Badly infested leaves may be cut away and thrown in the trash.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend "Take Down"; the active ingredients are canola oil and pyrethrin, which comes from a daisy relative.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend Medallion Fungicide.
  </s>
  <s>
   We also refer to this as nectar mold as it is feeding on the sugary nectar of the pitcher plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   It can often be wiped off of the pitchers with a damp paper towel and requires no treatment.
  </s>
  <s>
   ALGAE SLIME: Algae can grow in the trays of plants over time and is nonharmful but cleaning your trays once a month will inhibit this growth.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dogs can knock over pots and very rarely eat a plant or two.
  </s>
  <s>
   However, Zero Water pitchers will filter water enough and are an easy way to make small amounts of distilled water.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be watered using the tray method.
  </s>
  <s>
   Simply put your plants, in pitcher's pots, into a deep tray and fill it with pure water.
  </s>
  <s>
   SPECIES SPECIFIC CARE                                                                          American Pitcher Plants (Sarracenia)                                    If you have more questions or would like to see some of these care tips in action, check out our YouTube playlist All About Sarracenia!
  </s>
  <s>
   They will thrive in full sun, meaning at least six hours of direct light.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can grow pitcher indoors on a very, very sunny windowsill or in a terrarium under grow lights but pitcher generally do best outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   *If you see black mold on your pitcher, don't panic!
  </s>
  <s>
   This harmless mold grows on the pitcher nectar, and it is not harmful to your plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Although some consider it unsightly, it is totally normal and occurs on both plants in the wild and in cultivation.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be grown outdoors in full to part sun in mild climates.WATER: Use the tray method.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are tolerant of brief, light frost down to 25 F degrees, but may be killed in lower temperatures.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most terrestrials also do well in un-drained containers.
  </s>
  <s>
   The tighter, smaller leafed rosettes such a Pinguicula gypsicola or the bulb-like heterophylla and macrophylla require bone-dry conditions.
  </s>
  <s>
   Here is one all about potting up your plant after you receive it.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the spring and summer, large plants should be allowed to dry slightly before you water again.
  </s>
  <s>
   Wilting will damage roots and set the plant back.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dewy Pines are mediterranean natives.
  </s>
  <s>
   We ship our dewy pines in 4" round peat pot nestled into a protective plastic pot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Once liberated, you may put a few slits in the sides of the peat pot.
  </s>
  <s>
   This will help the roots find pitcher's way out, but is not necessary because the pot will quickly break down once planted.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not substitute the sand for perlite in this case.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sun Pitchers (Heliamphora)                                    SUN: Heliamphora like bright light.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown with less light, but pitcher will remain much greener.
  </s>
  <s>
   As summer approaches wait for the plant to quickly go brown.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical Pitcher Plants (Nepenthes)                                    SUN:  Most Nepenthes enjoy very bright, diffused light or partly sunny conditions.
  </s>
  <s>
   Put one pellet into each new pitcher as it opens.
  </s>
  <s>
   They will thrive in full sun, meaning at least six hours of direct light.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can grow pitcher indoors on a very, very sunny windowsill or in a terrarium under grow lights but pitcher generally do best outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   Also, if you grow pitcher indoors be sure to provide pitcher with a winter dormancy.WATER: Always keep pitcher sitting in a saucer with a few inches of distilled or purified water, pitcher do not want to dry out but try not to flood the top of the traps with water as pitcher do not appreciate this.
  </s>
  <s>
   Never let pitcher dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is a nice, mild, kelp-based food that won't burn your plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use MaxSea in the nursery and the plants love it!
  </s>
  <s>
   Lightly mist the leaves of the plants once a month for best results.
  </s>
  <s>
   Plants are also shipped throughout the year.
  </s>
  <s>
   In winter, it goes dormant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sarracenia The American Pitcher Plant comes in many shapes, sizes, and color.
  </s>
  <s>
   Full sun in spring and summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Dormant in winter.
  </s>
  <s>
   Full to partial sun during summer.
  </s>
  <s>
   In winter, pitcher drop pitcher's leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Grows best where summers are mild.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pinguicula Tropical plants with sticky, succulent-like leaves.
  </s>
  <s>
   Elevation (m)Avg Day Temperature (°C)Avg Night Temperature (°C)350016 - 224 - 12300017 - 237 - 14250018 - 249 - 15200020 - 2611 - 17150022 - 2813 - 19100024 - 3015 - 2150026 - 3217 - 23029 - 3520 - 26                    This is only an estimate - there are many other factors to consider, particularly for hybrids.
  </s>
  <s>
   NameLow (m)High (m)Region Nepenthes lamii27003520New GuineaNepenthes diatas24002900SumatraNepenthes angasanensis22002800SumatraNepenthes densiflora17003200SumatraNepenthes singalana20002900SumatraNepenthes macrophylla22002642BorneoNepenthes villosa16003240BorneoNepenthes putaiguneung22702370SumatraNepenthes lavicola20002600SumatraNepenthes diabolica22002300SulawesiNepenthes murudensis20002423BorneoNepenthes aristolochioides18002500SumatraNepenthes dubia16002700SumatraNepenthes edwardsiana16002700BorneoNepenthes talangensis18002500SumatraNepenthes lowii16502600BorneoNepenthes maryae20502150SulawesiNepenthes nigra15002700SulawesiNepenthes rajah15002650BorneoNepenthes inermis15002600SumatraNepenthes muluensis17002400BorneoNepenthes monticola14002620New GuineaNepenthes flava18002200SumatraNepenthes spathulata11002900Java, SumatraNepenthes hamata14002500SulawesiNepenthes jacquelineae17002200SumatraNepenthes jamban18002100SumatraNepenthes kitanglad18002100PhilippinesNepenthes mikei11002800SumatraNepenthes sumagaya16002247PhilippinesNepenthes lingulata17002100SumatraNepenthes ovata17002100SumatraNepenthes alba16002187Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes mantalingajanensis17002085PhilippinesNepenthes bongso10002700SumatraNepenthes glabrata16002100SulawesiNepenthes pectinata9502750SumatraNepenthes xiphioides18001900SumatraNepenthes mollis13002400BorneoNepenthes alzapan17501850PhilippinesNepenthes izumiae17001900SumatraNepenthes rhombicaulis16002000SumatraNepenthes robcantleyi17501850PhilippinesNepenthes spectabilis14002200SumatraNepenthes undulatifolia17501850SulawesiNepenthes fractiflexa14002150BorneoNepenthes copelandii11002400PhilippinesNepenthes naga15002000SumatraNepenthes berbulu14002100Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes barcelonae15001905PhilippinesNepenthes gracillima14002000Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes gymnamphora6002800Java, SumatraNepenthes stenophylla8002600BorneoNepenthes gantungensis16001784PhilippinesNepenthes ceciliae15001880PhilippinesNepenthes zygon15001875PhilippinesNepenthes petiolata14501900PhilippinesNepenthes argentii14001900PhilippinesNepenthes ephippiata13002000BorneoNepenthes zakriana8002500BorneoNepenthes pilosa15501650BorneoNepenthes pitopangii14001800SulawesiNepenthes nebularum14001800PhilippinesNepenthes attenboroughii14501726PhilippinesNepenthes macfarlanei15001657Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes mira15501605PhilippinesNepenthes appendiculata14501700BorneoNepenthes burkei11002000PhilippinesNepenthes pulchra13001800PhilippinesNepenthes sericea9002150Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes boschiana12001800BorneoNepenthes burbidgeae12001800BorneoNepenthes eymae10002000SulawesiNepenthes ventricosa10002000PhilippinesNepenthes fusca14001600BorneoNepenthes tentaculata4002550Borneo, SulawesiNepenthes adrianii9502000JavaNepenthes klossii9302000New GuineaNepenthes tboli14131513PhilippinesNepenthes paniculata14101510New GuineaNepenthes chaniana11001800BorneoNepenthes ramispina9002000Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes taminii9001950SumatraNepenthes glandulifera11001700BorneoNepenthes hamiguitanensis12001600PhilippinesNepenthes leonardoi13001490PhilippinesNepenthes pantaronensis13401440PhilippinesNepenthes sibuyanensis12501500PhilippinesNepenthes micramphora11001635PhilippinesNepenthes ulukaliana9001800Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes minima10001700SulawesiNepenthes maxima402600Maluku Islands, New Guinea, SulawesiNepenthes justinae10001620PhilippinesNepenthes rigidifolia10001600SumatraNepenthes negros12501350PhilippinesNepenthes peltata8651635PhilippinesNepenthes vogelii10001500BorneoNepenthes deaniana11801296PhilippinesNepenthes junghuhnii11701270SumatraNepenthes aenigma11501250PhilippinesNepenthes pudica11001300BorneoNepenthes longiptera7501600SumatraNepenthes palawanensis11001236PhilippinesNepenthes platychila9001400BorneoNepenthes alata5501650PhilippinesNepenthes dactylifera3001900BorneoNepenthes reinwardtiana02200Borneo, SumatraNepenthes tenuis10001200SumatraNepenthes tobaica3801800SumatraNepenthes ampullaria02100Borneo, Maluku Islands, New Guinea, Peninsular Malaysia, Singapore, Sumatra, ThailandNepenthes sanguinea3001800Peninsular Malaysia, ThailandNepenthes latiffiana10001100Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes ramos6701400PhilippinesNepenthes cabanae10001050PhilippinesNepenthes cornuta9501050PhilippinesNepenthes epiphytica9501050BorneoNepenthes faizaliana4001600BorneoNepenthes khasiana5001500IndiaNepenthes surigaoensis8001200PhilippinesNepenthes talaandig9501050PhilippinesNepenthes harauensis7001300SumatraNepenthes malimumuensis9701020PhilippinesNepenthes manobo9701020PhilippinesNepenthes bokorensis8001080CambodiaNepenthes domei8501000Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes adnata6001200SumatraNepenthes leyte850950PhilippinesNepenthes malayensis8001000Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes erucoides800929PhilippinesNepenthes eustachya01600SumatraNepenthes veitchii01600BorneoNepenthes cid720820PhilippinesNepenthes saranganiensis700800PhilippinesNepenthes benstonei1501350Peninsular MalaysiaNepenthes macrovulgaris3001200BorneoNepenthes mapuluensis700800BorneoNepenthes mirabilis01500Australia, Borneo, Cambodia, Java, Laos, Maluku Islands, New Guinea, Peninsular Malaysia, Philippines, Sulawesi, Sumatra, Thailand, Vietnam &amp; moreNepenthes smilesii01500Cambodia, Laos, Thailand, VietnamNepenthes truncata01500PhilippinesNepenthes bracteosa710760ThailandNepenthes weda4151014Maluku IslandsNepenthes clipeata600800BorneoNepenthes holdenii600800CambodiaNepenthes longifolia3001100SumatraNepenthes mindanaoensis01400PhilippinesNepenthes neoguineensis01400New GuineaNepenthes armin500850PhilippinesNepenthes abgracilis620720PhilippinesNepenthes hirsuta2001100BorneoNepenthes krabiensis600700ThailandNepenthes papuana01300New GuineaNepenthes graciliflora01280PhilippinesNepenthes rafflesiana01200Borneo, Peninsular Malaysia, Singapore, SumatraNepenthes halmahera01200Maluku IslandsNepenthes albomarginata01100Borneo, Peninsular Malaysia, SumatraNepenthes gracilis01100Borneo, Cambodia, Peninsular Malaysia, Singapore, Sulawesi, Sumatra, ThailandNepenthes merrilliana01100PhilippinesNepenthes pervillei350750SeychellesNepenthes thai500600ThailandNepenthes rosea450520ThailandNepenthes chang300600ThailandNepenthes hispida100800BorneoNepenthes kerrii400500ThailandNepenthes insignis0850New GuineaNepenthes vieillardii0850New CaledoniaNepenthes beccariana0800SumatraNepenthes bellii0800PhilippinesNepenthes extincta350450PhilippinesNepenthes sumatrana0800SumatraNepenthes bicalcarata0700BorneoNepenthes distillatoria0700Sri LankaNepenthes hirtella325375ThailandNepenthes kampotiana0600Cambodia, Thailand, VietnamNepenthes philippinensis0600PhilippinesNepenthes samar0600PhilippinesNepenthes alfedoi160345PhilippinesNepenthes madagascariensis0500MadagascarNepenthes northiana0500BorneoNepenthes tomoriana0500SulawesiNepenthes campanulata100300Borneo, Philippines Nepenthes masoalensis0400MadagascarNepenthes ultra0400PhilippinesNepenthes danseri0320Maluku IslandsNepenthes hemsleyana0200BorneoNepenthes suratensis0200ThailandNepenthes thorelii0200VietnamNepenthes rowaniae080AustraliaNepenthes tenax080AustraliaNepenthes treubiana080New GuineaNepenthes viridis050PhilippinesNepenthes parvula050AustraliaNepenthes abalata050PhilippinesNepenthes andamana050ThailandNepenthes kongkandana050ThailandNepenthes biak050New GuineaNepenthes orbiculata050ThailandNepenthes tayninhensis050VietnamNepenthes misoolensis050New Guinea       Looking to buy a tropical pitcher plant?
  </s>
  <s>
   If you’re in the UK, try South West Carnivorous Plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’d also highly recommend the following resources:  The Savage Garden, by Peter D’Amato.
  </s>
  <s>
   Available on Amazon.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes: The Tropical Pitcher Plants, Vols 1-3.
  </s>
  <s>
   © 2024 Tom’s Carnivores
  </s>
  <s>
   They will thrive in full sun, meaning at least six hours of direct light.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can grow pitcher indoors on a very, very sunny windowsill or in a terrarium under grow lights but pitcher generally do best outdoors.
  </s>
  <s>
   Also, if you grow pitcher indoors be sure to provide pitcher with a winter dormancy.WATER: Always keep pitcher sitting in a saucer with a few inches of distilled or purified water, pitcher do not want to dry out but try not to flood the top of the traps with water as pitcher do not appreciate this.
  </s>
  <s>
   Never let pitcher dry out.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend live meal worms available from any pet store.
  </s>
  <s>
   New to carnivorous plants?
  </s>
  <s>
   Start here!
  </s>
  <s>
   23 Jul 2023 If your pitcher plant is declining - leaves turning brown and crispy, growth dying - don't panic.
  </s>
  <s>
   Start here!
  </s>
  <s>
   23 Jul 2023 If your pitcher plant is declining - leaves turning brown and crispy, growth dying - don't panic.
  </s>
  <s>
   3 Aug 2022 If your tropical pitcher plant or 'monkey cup' isn't making new pitchers, you're not alone!
  </s>
  <s>
   This is one of the most common problems faced by growers.
  </s>
  <s>
   © 2024 Tom’s Carnivores
  </s>
  <s>
   My name’s Tom, and I run Tom’s Carnivores here at tomscarnivores.com.
  </s>
  <s>
   Qualifying purchases earn me a small commission:  In the UK, I recommend South West Carnivorous Plants in Devon.
  </s>
  <s>
   Your information will never be shared or sold to a 3rd party.
  </s>
  <s>
   Discover how to successfully cultivate tropical pitcher plants, also known as Monkey Cups, with my Complete Guide to Nepenthes Care.
  </s>
  <s>
   © 2024 Tom’s Carnivores
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical Pitcher Plants (Nepenthes)  If there is a royalty among carnivorous plants, that distinction surely lies with the Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Tropical pitcher plants have a rich botanical and horticultural history and the plants pitcherselves are a virtual ecosystem of give-and-take with nature.
  </s>
  <s>
   And nepenthes are hauntingly beautiful; nepenthes's pitcher traps often as elaborate and gaudy as artistic creations by humankind.
  </s>
  <s>
   This exotic carnivorous plant has a beautifully coloured cup shape and is therefore also called ‘Monkey Cup plant’.
  </s>
  <s>
   The purpose of these hairs is to prevent the prey from escaping.
  </s>
  <s>
   These forests have large temperature differences.
  </s>
  <s>
   However, there are also Monkey cup plants that grow in the wet lowlands.
  </s>
  <s>
   However, it is important that the plant is not in direct sunlight.
  </s>
  <s>
   In addition, the pitcher plant likes humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   However, it is important that the plant has space.
  </s>
  <s>
   Unlike the Venus flytrap and the Trumpet pitcher plant, Nepenthes does not need to hibernate.
  </s>
  <s>
   CHECK Available Carnivorous Plants Here &gt;&gt;                                        Welcome to South West Carnivorous Plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because of this, the carnivorous plant family has evolved to survive by luring insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous plants can be found all over the world.
  </s>
  <s>
   When an insect enters the cup, it can not come out again.
  </s>
  <s>
   This trap owes its name from its beautiful appearance.
  </s>
  <s>
   Similar to the cup trap, this trap produces an attractive liquid and beautiful colour that attracts insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   Inside the trap are small vertical slits that prevent the insect from escaping.
  </s>
  <s>
   The trap consists of a leaf covered with sticky droplets that smell delicious.
  </s>
  <s>
   The prey insect cannot move.
  </s>
  <s>
   Remove the traps carefully with clean secateurs without damaging the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   These flowers aim to attract more insects and can therefore continue to bloom nicely.RepottingDuring a year Carnivorous plants will have a growth and a dormancy period.
  </s>
  <s>
   The growth period starts in spring to autumn (around April to around August).
  </s>
  <s>
   During this period, it is best to repot carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes - also known as tropical pitcher plants or monkey cups - have been inspiring awe in botanists since flytrap were first discovered by Europeans in the 17th century.
  </s>
  <s>
   With pitcher's dazzling colours and elaborately decorative traps, the plants seem to flaunt pitcher's carnivory with pride.
  </s>
  <s>
   Light Most tropical pitcher plants grow in the upper canopy of the rainforest and prefer very bright light, but without much direct sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   For highlanders, this means warm days and cool nights, e.g.
  </s>
  <s>
   20-25°C (68-77°F) during the day and 10-15°C (50-59°F) at night.
  </s>
  <s>
   For lowlanders, you’ll need hot days and warm nights, e.g.
  </s>
  <s>
   closer to 30°C (86°F) days and 20°C (68°F) nights.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cold snaps can be lethal.
  </s>
  <s>
   One very important thing to note is that hybrids are generally far more temperature-tolerant than pure species.
  </s>
  <s>
   A lack of inflating pitchers on your plant can be a sign of insufficient humidity.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many growing guides suggest that 80-90% is optimal, but I’ve found that keeping the air so close to saturation can lead to issues with mould and fungus, particularly with low airflow.
  </s>
  <s>
   But if you are successful in cultivating these plants, space can quickly become a problem.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most Nepenthes are climbing or scrambling vines, and when pitcher reach maturity some species can put out nearly a meter of stem per year!
  </s>
  <s>
   Collecting and breeding tropical pitcher plants can easily become an addiction!
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ventricosa x lowii: Also known as N. x briggsiana, this hybrid is a fast grower with red, woody pitchers and an attractively striped peristome.
  </s>
  <s>
   A great alternative to the more common N. x ventrata.
  </s>
  <s>
   It has small, tubby, scarlet pitchers on glossy green leaves, and can grow into a very bushy plant!
  </s>
  <s>
   N. ‘Gaya’: A vigorous grower with red and yellow speckled pitchers, this cultivar is N. khasiana x (ventricosa x maxima).
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes attenboroughii pitcher, growing in my ultramafic mix of peat, perlite, and kanuma.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes attenboroughii pitcher.
  </s>
  <s>
   Watering Nepenthes Tropical pitcher plants benefit from frequent watering.
  </s>
  <s>
   Whereas North American pitcher plants (Sarracenia) will quickly deteriorate if given hard water from the tap, tropical pitcher plants do not seem to mind as much.
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve even seen mineral deposits build up on leaves, and the plants didn’t seem to mind.
  </s>
  <s>
   These should be small enough to fit comfortably inside the pitcher.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not overfeed, or your plant’s pitchers may turn black and rot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Flowers &amp; Seeds Tropical pitcher plants are native to equatorial regions that have fairly stable conditions year-round.
  </s>
  <s>
   These look very different from normal leaves and pitchers - a bit like a miniature corn cob.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Savage Garden, by Peter D’Amato.
  </s>
  <s>
   Available on Amazon.
  </s>
  <s>
   © 2024 Tom’s Carnivores
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes Tropical                                                                                Books Ideas Submission Bespoke Publishing Service About Documentaries Expeditions           Select Page                                                                                        Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants Volumes 1, 2 &amp; 3    £149.97   Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants is a seminal, three volume work that documents all currently recognised species of Nepenthes for the first time.
  </s>
  <s>
   All copies are signed by Stewart McPherson.
  </s>
  <s>
   DESCRIPTION Fifteen years in the making and the result of more than two hundred research expeditions, Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants is a three volume work that documents all 192 currently recognised species of Nepenthes for the first time.
  </s>
  <s>
   Over 2,250 pages, (each volume being approx.
  </s>
  <s>
   With contributions from experts across the globe, filled with brand new discoveries Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants showcases the full diversity and astoundingly intricate beauty of the tropical pitcher plants for the very first time.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants is specifically designed to complement Stewart McPherson’s past books: New Nepenthes Volume 1 and New Nepenthes Volume 2.
  </s>
  <s>
   All three volumes of Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants are sold as a set.
  </s>
  <s>
   All copies are signed by Stewart McPherson.
  </s>
  <s>
   DOWNLOAD PDF  For the benefit of researchers and the Nepenthes taxonomists, Redfern Natural History Productions is publicly releasing the description of two new species (N. sericea and N. ulukaliana) described in Nepenthes – The Tropical Pitcher Plants Volumes 1, 2 and 3.
  </s>
 </pitcher>
 <fertilizer synset="fertilizer.n.01">
  <s>
   Be cautious with fertilizers that have not been carefully tested on carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most fertilizers are too strong for these plants and may severely damage or even kill fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use fertilizers that have been recommended by experts who have tested fertilizer first.We have found MaxSea fertilizer to be the most gentle and effective.
  </s>
  <s>
   Add a pellet of Osmocote slow release fertilizer (14-14-14) to pitcher plants; Sarracenia, Cephalotus, Helimaphora and Nepenthes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sometimes pitcher do lightly burn the sides of the pitchers where pitcher come to rest inside of the pitchers but this is not harmful long term and often can be avoided if a bit of distilled water is added at the same time as the pellet.We use Schultz cactus fertilizer on the Pinguicula, applying to the leaves only and following the instructions on the packaging for dilution.
  </s>
  <s>
   PESTS, PESTICIDES, DISEASES AND PETS                                                                    Unfortunately and ironically, carnivorous plants may be afflicted with almost all of the same pests as normal plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Our plants can be damaged by some pesticides and many are very toxic, but we have a few things that we know are safe for the plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   Before you spray, isolate the infected plants.APHIDS: The constant sap sucking of aphids will cause the new leaves of sundews and pitcher plants to twist and contort as fertilizer grow.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be careful and do not use Miracle-Gro brand peat and perlite as it has been fortified with fertilizers and will harm carnivorous plants!SAND: We recommend using washed horticultural from a local garden store.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you cannot find that you can often find large lava rock in a hardware or garden center with other decorative rocks.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be sure to wet the perlite before use as you do not want to inhale the dust from perlite.
  </s>
  <s>
   PINGUICULA MIX: For Temperate species: Use Peat and Perlite mix.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can still supplement with a foliar fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Apply MaxSea fertilizer once per month to the foliage and into the pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be grown outdoors year-round in mild areas.DORMANCY: No dormancy needed.SOIL: Cephalotus thrive in a mix if two parts sand and/or perlite to one part peat.FERTILIZER/FEEDING:  MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves and pitchers of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Osmocote slow release fertilizer pellets can also be added to pitchers.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers add dolomite or gypsum to this, although we have not found it necessary.
  </s>
  <s>
   But when it's handy, add an additional part of lava rock or pumice.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may also be grown in a Nepenthes mix.FERTILIZER/FEEDING: Temperate species grown outdoors will catch fertilizer's own food.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use Schultz cactus fertilizer on our Mexican and Tropical Pinguicula, applying to the leaves only and following the instructions on the packaging for dilution.
  </s>
  <s>
   Gently slide the peat pot out of the plastic pot it was shipped in, if it resists, you may cut away the plastic pot with heavy kitchen shears or pruners.
  </s>
  <s>
   This allows you to transplant your little dewy pine without disturbing pitcher's sensitive roots.FERTILIZER/FEEDING:  MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can also add an additional part of perlite, lava rock or pumice.
  </s>
  <s>
   Always use drained containers.FERTILIZER/FEEDING: MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves and pitchers of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Osmocote 16-16-16 fertilizer pellets are also a wonderful addition to your fertilizer routine.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can still supplement with a foliar fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Apply MaxSea fertilizer once per month to the foliage only.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you would like to feed the traps of your flytrap it is recommended that you use live prey as the traps usually require continued movement from fertilizer's food to stimulate the full absorption process.
  </s>
  <s>
   They will often open too soon if fertilizer are fed inert foods and will not absorb nutrients.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is a 4 ounce jar of MaxSea 16-16-16 fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   We recommend against using this for the Pinguicula and instead recommend using Schultz Cactus Fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can still supplement with a foliar fertilizer.
  </s>
  <s>
   Apply MaxSea fertilizer once per month to the foliage only.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you would like to feed the traps of your flytrap it is recommended that you use live prey as the traps usually require continued movement from fertilizer's food to stimulate the full absorption process.
  </s>
  <s>
   They will often open too soon if fertilizer are fed inert foods and will not absorb nutrients.
  </s>
  <s>
   The cup contains enzymes that slowly digest the insect.
  </s>
  <s>
   So-called intermediates sit somewhere in-between, while hybrids depend on the preference of the parent species.
  </s>
  <s>
   This means that if you can’t provide sufficiently cool nights, your best bet is to try a hybrid or a tolerant intermediate.
  </s>
  <s>
   I use a foliar spray that doubles as a natural pesticide, and apply it every 2 weeks in the growing season - it’s available on Amazon.
  </s>
  <s>
   As with all carnivorous plants, remember that food and fertiliser should be near the end of your priority list!
  </s>
  <s>
   No fertiliser is better than too much.
  </s>
 </fertilizer>
 <sphagnum synset="sphagnum.n.01">
  <s>
   Each species requires it's own specific blend but most carnivorous plants should be grown in some mix of peat moss, perlite, long fibered New Zealand sphagnum moss or sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you can't find horticultural sand you can use the sand used for children's sand boxes, called play sand.NEW ZEALAND LONG-FIBERED SPHAGNUM MOSS: We use New Zealand long-fibered Sphagnum moss as a base for many of our other plants such as Nepenthes and Heliamphora.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many retail garden centers and nurseries unwittingly sell Oregon green moss as Sphagnum moss.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are not the same, in fact Oregon green moss will kill our plants if it is used.DOMESTIC LONG-FIBERED SPHAGNUM MOSS: We use domestic long-fibered sphagnum to line the bottoms of our pots to prevent the peat and perlite from seeping out.PERLITE: This can be found in many hardware stores and specialty nurseries.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use a mix of three parts New Zealand long-fibered Sphagnum moss to one part of the coarse materials, perlite, orchid bark and pumice.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can also use tree-fern fiber, lava rock or charcoal for your coarse materials.DROSOPHYLLUM MIX: We use a mix composed of equal parts perlite, pumice, peat moss, and sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   DARLINGTONIA MIX: The best mix for Cobra plants is three parts New Zealand long-fibered sphagnum moss to one part pumice or lava rock.
  </s>
  <s>
   Live sphagnum makes an ideal media as well.HELIAMPHORA MIX: Use a mix comprised of mostly New Zealand long-fibered sphagnum moss with some pumice or lava rock mixed in.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown in live sphagnum also, but take care that it doesn't overwhelm the Heliamphora.
  </s>
  <s>
   We use a mix composed of equal parts perlite, pumice, peat moss, coarse vermiculite, and sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   The bigger the pot the better, as flytrap's mass will resist warming.DORMANCY: No dormancy is required.SOIL: Use a mix comprised of mostly New Zealand long-fibered sphagnum moss with some pumice or lava rock mixed in.
  </s>
  <s>
   They may be grown in live sphagnum also, but take care that it doesn't overwhelm the Heliamphora.FERTILIZER/FEEDING:  MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves and pitchers of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   The best are about three parts New Zealand long-fibered Sphagnum moss to one part of some combination of coarse materials, such as perlite, orchid bark, pumice, tree-fern fiber, lava rock or charcoal.FERTILIZER/FEEDING:  MaxSea fertilizer can also be applied, once per month, to the leaves and into the pitchers of the plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Even the live sphagnum thrives with MaxSea!
  </s>
  <s>
   The moss retains water easily and translocates nutrients effortlessly for timely release to the plant without accumulating unwanted soluble salts; management costs decrease and plant health improves.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can also make your own compost mix with peat (maximum pH of 5), sphagnum moss, grit and perlite.Need more information?Would you like to learn more about carnivorous plants?
  </s>
  <s>
   Popular mixtures tend to include a combination of long-fibered sphagnum moss, orchid bark, tree fern fiber, coconut husk fiber, sand, perlite, and pumice rock in varying ratios.
  </s>
  <s>
   Many growers successfully grow sphagnum's highlanders in pure long-fibered sphagnum moss.
  </s>
  <s>
   As a general rule, however, a mixture of long-fibered sphagnum moss, perlite, and - optionally - orchid bark works well.
  </s>
  <s>
   sphagnum, perlite, etc).
  </s>
 </sphagnum>
 <soil synset="territory.n.03">
  <s>
   Unglazed terracotta pots are very porous and dry the soil out quickly.
  </s>
  <s>
   Also, soil may leach salts out into the soil with time.
  </s>
  <s>
   FERTILIZERS AND FEEDING                                    Carnivorous plants evolved to catch insects to get the fertilizers that are lacking in sundew's soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   There are virtually no nutrients available in soil's planting media, so carnivores need to eat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Apply to the leaves only, do not pour through the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Organic does not mean non-toxic.FUNGUS GNATS: The adult fungus gnats will lay flytrap's eggs in the soil of many houseplants, including carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   The larvae in the soil can be detrimental to the plants though as drosera feed on roots.
  </s>
  <s>
   This will kill the larvae in the soil.DEER: While deer may take an exploratory nibble of a Sarracenia care rarely come back for seconds and overall leave the plants alone long term.BIRDS: Birds can be destructive of bog containers because care occasionally poke care's beaks into the wet soil, looking for food like worms.
  </s>
  <s>
   If soil are a continuous problem you can insert bamboo skewers, pointy side up, into the soil to discourage birds from landing in the pots.RACCOONS: Because the outdoor plants like to sit in water, raccoons can be attracted to the pots.
  </s>
  <s>
   Sometimes soil will play in the water or dig out the plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is fairly rare and you can try sprinkling cayenne pepper on the soil to discourage soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can also try the skewer method and bury skewers, pointy side out into the soil to stop soil from getting into the soil.BOTRYTIS: This is a fungus that often looks like fuzzy bread mold.
  </s>
  <s>
   This is a totally harmless mold, very common and even seen in the wild on the plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   On the surface of the soil of bog plants, algae slime will sometimes grow.
  </s>
  <s>
   If it is unsightly, scrape it off the surface of the soil with a spoon.PETS: Cats sometimes like to like the dew off of sundews or take a nibble.
  </s>
  <s>
   SOILS                                                                    We offer both individual ingredients and mixes for all your carnivorous plant needs which can be found in our Growing Supplies section.
  </s>
  <s>
   Never pot sphagnum into regular garden or potting soil; this will kill sphagnum.BASIC INGREDIENTSPEAT MOSS: We use professional grade peat moss only.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be sure to rinse you lava rock before use.ORCHID BARK: We prefer to use a small, fine particle high quality orchid bark of 3/8-1/4 inch size.SOIL MIXESYou can buy our pre-made, small batch, custom soil mixes online but if you would like to source ingredients locally you can make your own mixes at home.PEAT AND PERLITE MIX: Four parts peat moss to one part perlite.
  </s>
  <s>
   This mix is suitable for Sarracenia, most Drosera, Dionaea and Temperate Pinguicula.NEPENTHES MIX: Nepenthes enjoy loose, open soil that remains wet to moist but allows drainage of excess water.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are tolerant of a wide variety of soil mixes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm temperate varieties do well in a soil of one part peat to one part sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican and tropical species enjoy a more open mix of equal parts sand, perlite, pumice and peat.CEPHALOTUS AND BYBLIS MIX: These will thrive in a mix if two parts sand and/or perlite to one part peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Total dissolved solids (TDS) are best if below 150 parts per million (PPM).
  </s>
  <s>
   You can purchase an inexpensive TDS meter on Amazon to test your water.Locally; Santa Rosa city, Guerneville city, East Bay MUD, some municipal water &amp; Sacramento area water that comes from the river may be used on carnivorous plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   They should be grown outdoors (year-round in areas with mild winters) if possible.
  </s>
  <s>
   Growing seed in an in-ground bog will help insulate seed as well.Lastly you can remove the plants from seed's pots, gently clean the roots of soil, wrap the roots in a bit of damp long-fibered New Zealand sphagnum moss, place the plants in a seal-able bag and put the bag into the refrigerator.
  </s>
  <s>
   Leave soil in the refrigerator for at least six weeks or until night time temperatures in your area are consistently over 32 F, periodically checking on soil to make sure soil are still a bit moist and are not growing any fungus.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pot soil back up when you remove soil from the fridge.SOIL: We prefer a mix of four parts fertilizer free peat moss to one part perlite.FEEDING AND FERTILIZER: When grown outdoors Sarracenia will catch plenty of food and do not need supplementation.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are best grown in cool highland greenhouse or terrariums.
  </s>
  <s>
   Bladderworts (Utricularia)                                    SUN: Full to part sun.WATER: Use the tray method for terrestrial and tropical bladderworts, keeping the soil wet.TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY: There are 200 plus species of Bladderworts and fertilizer grow virtually worldwide, thus fertilizer come from varied climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   The terrestrial bladderworts make wonderful, miniature, flowering ground covers in the spaces around your other carnivores and can take temperature from 40-90 degrees.SOIL: Plastic containers with drainage holes work best for terrestrial and epiphytic species.
  </s>
  <s>
   When the rosettes change to flytrap's small succulents in winter, keep the soil on the dry side, dampening flytrap only slightly and occasionally.
  </s>
  <s>
   Species with larger winter leaves, like a few of the moranensis varieties or agnata, enjoy winters soils just slightly damp.
  </s>
  <s>
   Cuban species should be kept wet year-round, with only slight winter drying.TEMPERATURE:  As butterworts grow worldwide, soil come from varied climates.
  </s>
  <s>
   Temperate Pinguicula need cold winters while soil are dormant to thrive.
  </s>
  <s>
   They do best outdoors in areas with mild winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican Butterworts do well in terrariums, greenhouses and windowsillsDORMANCY:  Mexican or Tropical butterworts have a winter dormancy that is marked by a change in the leaves from soil's carnivorous type to a tighter, more succulent leaf.
  </s>
  <s>
   Warm temperate varieties do well in a soil of one part peat to one part sand.
  </s>
  <s>
   Mexican and tropical species enjoy a more open mix of equal parts sand, perlite, vermiculite, and peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Do not allow pitcher to dry out so much that wilting occurs, but the soil can get surprisingly dry before this happens.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be grown easily outdoors year-round in California and the Southwest or anywhere else with hot dry summers and rainy winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   Plant your dewy pine into a large terracotta clay pot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid pouring through the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Keep the soil damp but not permanently waterlogged.TEMPERATURE: The rainbow plant does best best in tropical climates, but its annual nature allows you to grow it during any span of several months of warm weather.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are great little terrarium plants.DORMANCY: Dry summer dormancy is not necessary in cultivation.SOIL: Rainbow plants thrive in a mix of two parts sand and one part peat.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid pouring through the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   In a terrarium, high powered fluorescent light should be used and we recommend a fixture with four T-5 bulbs.WATER: Use the tray method, keeping the soil damp to wet year round.
  </s>
  <s>
   Keep the soil cool by watering with cold water, (refrigerated water is quite helpful on warm summer days).TEMPERATURE: With the exception of the lowland form of Heliamphora heterodoxa, all Heliamphora come from high plateaus called the Tepuis, in Venezuela.
  </s>
  <s>
   It is cool and misty all year, so soil require bright light, without ever heating up.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid pouring through the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   If your sundew is not producing dew it most likely needs more light.WATER: Most sundews thrive on the tray method, which keeps the soil permanently wet.
  </s>
  <s>
   Winter growing species require periods of complete summer dormancy, at which time the soil has to be dried out.
  </s>
  <s>
   Misting will not provide enough moisture for this plant, be sure to pour water through the pot and soil mix frequently to make sure all the mix remains moist.TEMPERATURE AND DORMANCY:  All Nepenthes are tropical plants, roughly divided into two categories called lowlanders and highlanders.
  </s>
  <s>
   They can be damaged or killed by temperatures below 50 F and in direct sun outdoors in high heat.Here is a very handy guide to Nepenthes temperature range by species: The Nepenthes GuideSOIL: Nepenthes enjoy loose, open soil that remains wet to moist but allows drainage of excess water.
  </s>
  <s>
   They are tolerant of a wide variety of soil mixes.
  </s>
  <s>
   Avoid pouring through the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   They should be grown outdoors year-round in areas with mild winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   The third option is to remove the plants from seed's pots, gently clean the roots of soil, wrap the roots in a bit of damp long-fibered New Zealand sphagnum moss, place the plants in a seal-able bag and put the bag into the refrigerator.
  </s>
  <s>
   Leave soil in the refrigerator from October to February, periodically checking on soil to make sure soil are still a bit moist and are not growing any fungus.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pot soil back up in February.
  </s>
  <s>
   SOIL: We prefer a mix of four parts fertilizer free peat moss to one part perlite.FEEDING AND FERTILIZER: When grown outdoors Venus flytraps will catch plenty of food and do not need supplementation.
  </s>
  <s>
   Growing Supplies Carnivorous plants require specialized soil mixes, fertilizers and even pots!
  </s>
  <s>
   We have compiled a collection of all of the things we prefer to use in the greenhouse; from pots to fungicides to customized soil blends!
  </s>
  <s>
   Their small bladders feed on various swimming and crawling creatures that inhabit utricularia's soil like fungus gnat larvae and tiny worms.
  </s>
  <s>
   They produce carpets of short stolons along the soil surface that look like tiny blades of grass pressed flat to the ground.
  </s>
  <s>
   Full to partial sun.
  </s>
  <s>
   Soil: General Mix Use this mix for Venus Flytraps, Sundews, and Sarracenia.
  </s>
  <s>
   Soil: Tropical Pitcher Plant Mix Use this for Nepenthes, Heliamphora, Brocchinia, and Cephalotus.
  </s>
  <s>
   For more general Nepenthes cultivation advice including water, light, and soil, head over to my Tropical Pitcher Plant Care Guide.
  </s>
  <s>
   If you’re interested in learning about general Nepenthes cultivation, such as soil preferences, light levels, and water, I recommend you check out my Complete Guide to Tropical Pitcher Plants.
  </s>
  <s>
   They should be grown outdoors year-round in areas with mild winters.
  </s>
  <s>
   The third option is to remove the plants from seed's pots, gently clean the roots of soil, wrap the roots in a bit of damp long-fibered New Zealand sphagnum moss, place the plants in a seal-able bag and put the bag into the refrigerator.
  </s>
  <s>
   Leave soil in the refrigerator from October to February, periodically checking on soil to make sure soil are still a bit moist and are not growing any fungus.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pot soil back up in February.
  </s>
  <s>
   SOIL: We prefer a mix of four parts fertilizer free peat moss to one part perlite.FEEDING AND FERTILIZER: When grown outdoors Venus flytraps will catch plenty of food and do not need supplementation.
  </s>
  <s>
   Each profile page includes advice on successful cultivation, photos of my plants (and of specimens in the wild where possible), and information on where to buy .
  </s>
  <s>
   Learn how to properly care for your Venus flytrap with this complete care guide covering water, light, soil, and dormancy.
  </s>
  <s>
   All Besgrow Spagmoss is harvested from sustainable and renewable wetlands on the pristine West Coast of New Zealand’s South Island.
  </s>
  <s>
   This means you can be confident that the highest quality Besgrow Spagmoss will always be available for you and for your plants without damaging our children’s natural wetlands.
  </s>
  <s>
   The digestive juices are produced by glands located on that inside of the cup.
  </s>
  <s>
   Due to its carnivorous properties, Nepenthes is able to live on nutrient-poor soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   The catching cups can be low on the ground or, on the contrary, hang high in a tree.
  </s>
  <s>
   In the lowlands, it is warm both day and night.
  </s>
  <s>
   Did you know that carnivorous plants evolved in such a way that seed do not use soil as a source of nutrition, but insects?Insect-eating plantsCarnivorous plants are true carnivores and eat all kinds of insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   In nature, carnivorous plants grow in swampy areas and jungles.
  </s>
  <s>
   These areas have nutrient-less soil, meaning there is no nutrition in the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Carnivorous plants are used indoors as natural fly control, or outdoors in a bog garden for example.
  </s>
  <s>
   Most carnivorous plant species need a lot of water.
  </s>
  <s>
   Because carnivorous plants cannot extract substances from the soil properly, it is difficult to separate the substances (which can cause roots to rot).
  </s>
  <s>
   As a result, the carnivorous plant absorbs all substances from the soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Read more about watering carnivorous plants here.LightCarnivorous plants generally need a lot of sunlight.
  </s>
  <s>
   Lots of light gives soil a beautiful colour and allows carnivorous plants to attract more insects.
  </s>
  <s>
   Read how much light each species needs on our downloadable care guides for carnivorous plants.SoilCarnivorous plants are on nutrient-less soil in nature.
  </s>
  <s>
   As a result, soil need special carnivorous plant soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Preferably do not use normal potting soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Flowering costs a lot of energy for a carnivorous plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Preferably use special carnivorous plant soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   Their habitats are hugely diverse, and some are far more adaptable growers than others.
  </s>
  <s>
   I find it’s just as effective to water little and often, to keep the soil moist.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can monitor your humidity using a SensorPush unit, available on Amazon.
  </s>
  <s>
   It’s particularly adaptable to lower humidity environments, a trait often passed to its hybrid offspring - so look out for hybrids with this species.
  </s>
  <s>
   Soil for Nepenthes Nepenthes are very tolerant when it comes to soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   They enjoy a loose, low-nutrition growing medium which keeps soil's roots aerated and allows excess water to quickly drain away while still retaining some moisture.
  </s>
  <s>
   Exactly how coarse your soil should be is dependent on numerous other factors, including ambient humidity, frequency of watering, and the species and age of your plant.
  </s>
  <s>
   Certain more challenging species - including some rare highland and ultra-highland Nepenthes - often benefit from a specific mixture which reflects soil's natural habitat (e.g.
  </s>
  <s>
   whether soil grow terrestrially or as an ephiphyte).
  </s>
  <s>
   Aim to keep the soil damp at all times and never let it dry out completely.
  </s>
  <s>
   Unlike many other carnivores, Nepenthes are not bog plants and do not appreciate having waterlogged soil.
  </s>
  <s>
   As such, avoid standing soil in water for extended periods, since this can cause root rot.
  </s>
  <s>
   Some growers stand soil's pots on a layer of plastic egg crate, which helps excess water drain away.
  </s>
  <s>
   That said, impurities can build up over time and will often accelerate the breakdown of your soil mixture.
  </s>
 </soil>
 <veitchii>
  <s>
   Nepenthes tropical pitcher plants Nepenthes species      Nepenthes aristolochioides     Nepenthes attenboroughii     Nepenthes edwardsiana     Nepenthes ephippiata     Nepenthes hamata     Nepenthes jamban     Nepenthes lowii     Nepenthes macrophylla     Nepenthes maxima     Nepenthes mollis     Nepenthes rajah     Nepenthes robcantleyi     Nepenthes singalana     Nepenthes veitchii     Nepenthes ventricosa   Nepenthes Hybrids      Nepenthes (lowii × veitchii) × burbidgeae     Nepenthes hamata × edwardsiana     Nepenthes rajah × (burbidgeae × edwardsiana)     Nepenthes truncata × ephippiata     Nepenthes veitchii × burbidgeae     Nepenthes veitchii × lowii     Nepenthes veitchii × platychila   Dionaea Coming soon!
  </s>
  <s>
   I’ve found N. ‘Gaya’, N. ‘Bloody Mary’, and N. x ventrata to be particularly forgiving in this regard, along with hybrids involving hairy species like N. veitchii.
  </s>
  <s>
   Pitcher on Nepenthes veitchii x burbidgeae holding over a pint of liquid.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes veitchii x burbidgeae starting to climb.
  </s>
  <s>
   You can try to source smaller species such as N. glabrata, or slower growers like N. veitchii.
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes veitchii.
  </s>
  <s>
   N. veitchii: A beautiful species and one of my favourites, N. veitchii has traps with wide peristomes and is covered in fuzzy brown hair.
  </s>
  <s>
   Be sure to check out my profile of Nepenthes veitchii!
  </s>
  <s>
   Nepenthes veitchii x platychila.
  </s>
  <s>
   All 192 recognised species of Nepenthes are documented in this work, namely: Nepenthes abalata, N. abgracilis, N. adnata, N. adrianii, N. aenigma, N. alata, N. alba, N. albomarginata, N. alfredoi, N. alzapan, N. ampullaria , N. andamana, N. angasanensis, N. appendiculata, N. argentii, N. aristolochioides, N. armin, N. attenboroughii, N. barcelonae, N. beccariana, N. bellii, N. benstonei, N. berbulu, N. biak, N. bicalcarata, N. bokorensis, N. bongso, N. boschiana, N. bracteosa, N. burbidgeae, N. burkei, N. cabanae, N. campanulata, N. candalaga, N. ceciliae, N. chang, N. chaniana, N. cid, N. clipeata, N. copelandii, N. cornuta, N. dactylifera, N. danseri, N. deaniana, N. densiflora, N. diabolica, N. diatas, N. distillatoria, N. domei, N. dubia, N. edwardsiana, N. ephippiata, N. epiphytica, N. erucoides, N. eustachya, N. eymae, N. faizaliana, N. flava, N. fractiflexa, N. fusca, N. gantungensis, N. glabrata, N. glandulifera, N. graciliflora, N. gracilis, N. gracillima, N. gymnamphora, N. halmahera, N. hamata, N. hamiguitanensis, N. harauensis, N. hemsleyana, N. hirsuta, N. hirtella, N. hispida, N. holdenii, N. inermis, N. insignis, N. izumiae, N. jacquelineae, N. jamban, N. justinae, N. kampotiana, N. kerrii, N. khasiana, N. kitanglad, N. klossii, N. kongkandana, N. krabiensis, N. lamii, N. latiffiana, N. lavicola, N. leonardoi, N. leyte, N. lingulata, N. longifolia, N. longiptera, N. lowii, N. macfarlanei, N. macrophylla, N. macrovulgaris, N. madagascariensis, N. malayensis, N. malimumuensis, N. manobo, N. mantalingajanensis, N. mapuluensis, N. maryae, N. masoalensis, N. maxima, N. maximoides, N. merrilliana, N. micramphora, N. mikei, N. mindanaoensis, N. mira, N. mirabilis, N. misoolensis, N. mollis, N. monticola, N. muluensis, N. murudensis, N. naga, N. nebularum, N. negros, N. neoguineensis, N. nigra, N. northiana, N. orbiculata, N. ovata, N. palawanensis, N. paniculata, N. pantaronensis, N. papuana, N. parvula, N. peltata, N. pervillei, N. petiolata, N. philippinensis, N. pilosa, N. pitopangii, N. platychila, N. pudica, N. pulchra, N. putaiguneung, N. rafflesiana, N. rajah, N. ramispina, N. ramos, N. reinwardtiana, N. rhombicaulis, N. rigidifolia, N. rosea, N. rowaniae, N. samar, N. sanguinea, N. saranganiensis, N. sericea, N. sibuyanensis, N. singalana, N. smilesii, N. spathulata, N. spectabilis, N. stenophylla, N. sumagaya, N. sumatrana, N. suratensis, N. surigaoensis, N. talaandig, N. talangensis, N. taminii, N. tboli, N. tenax, N. tentaculata, N. tenuis, N. thai, N. thorelii, N. tobaica, N. tomoriana, N. treubiana, N. truncata, N. ultra, N. ulukaliana, N. undulatifolia, N. veitchii, N. ventricosa, N. vieillardii, N. villosa, N. viridis, N. vogelii, N. weda and N. zakriana.
  </s>
 </veitchii>
 <muscipula>
  <s>
   Its Latin name Dionaea muscipula partly commemorates Venus, the goddess of beauty.
  </s>
  <s>
   We have been growing carnivorous plants since 1990 and specialise in hardy carnivorous plants including Venus Flytrap (Dionaea muscipula), North American Trumpet Pitcher Plants (Sarracenia), Sundews (Drosera) and Cobra Lily (Darlingtonia), Bladderworts (Utricularia) and more.
  </s>
  <s>
   The Venus Flytrap (Dionaea muscipula) is the only plant species that can count.
  </s>
 </muscipula>
</kb>
